<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sathan inthron'd in his chair of pestilence. Or, Quakerism in its exaltation. Being a true narrative and relation of the manner of James Nailer (that eminent Quaker's) entrance into the city of Bristoll the 24. day of October, 1656. With one man going bare-headed before him: and two women; one on one side, another on the other side of his horse, holding the reines, and leading him. Singing, Hosannah, and Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Israel. Together with some blasphemous letters found about him, with their examinations thereupon, in this city, and other considerable passages, and observations. Whereto is added a vindication of the magistrates and inhabitants of this city, in reference to the nestling of these Quakers amongst us. With a declaration of the occasion, rise and growth of them in this city. / Collected and published by Ra. Farmer, a servant of (and that hopes to be saved by) that Jesus Christ who was crucified at Jerusalem above sixteen hundred yeares agoe: whom the Quakers nullifie.</title>
            <author>Farmer, Ralph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85122</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862486</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114647</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240902168</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E897_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862486</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862486e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114647)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E897[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sathan inthron'd in his chair of pestilence. Or, Quakerism in its exaltation. Being a true narrative and relation of the manner of James Nailer (that eminent Quaker's) entrance into the city of Bristoll the 24. day of October, 1656. With one man going bare-headed before him: and two women; one on one side, another on the other side of his horse, holding the reines, and leading him. Singing, Hosannah, and Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Israel. Together with some blasphemous letters found about him, with their examinations thereupon, in this city, and other considerable passages, and observations. Whereto is added a vindication of the magistrates and inhabitants of this city, in reference to the nestling of these Quakers amongst us. With a declaration of the occasion, rise and growth of them in this city. / Collected and published by Ra. Farmer, a servant of (and that hopes to be saved by) that Jesus Christ who was crucified at Jerusalem above sixteen hundred yeares agoe: whom the Quakers nullifie.</title>
                  <author>Farmer, Ralph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Thomas, and are to be sold at his house in Green-Arbor.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657. [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 18"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Thomason apparently received his copy in 1656.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Naylor, James, 1617?-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  England --  Bristol --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114647:1"/>
            <p>SATHAN Inthron'd in his Chair of <hi>PESTILENCE.</hi> OR, <hi>Quakerism in its Exaltation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a true Narrative and Relation of the manner of <hi>James Nailer</hi> (that eminent Quaker's) entrance into the City of <hi>Bristoll</hi> the 24 day of <hi>October,</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With one man going bare-headed before him: And two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; one on one side, another on the other side of his horse, holding the reines, and leading him. Singing,</hi> Hosannah, <hi>and</hi> Holy, Holy, Holy, <hi>Lord God of</hi> Israel.</p>
            <p>Together with some blasphemous letters found about him, with their examinations thereupon, in this City, and other considerable passages, and observations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereto is added a Vindication of the Magistrates and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this City, in reference to the nestling of these Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers amongst us. With a Declaration of the occasion, rise and growth of them in this City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected and Published by <hi>Ra. Farmer,</hi> a servant of (and that hopes to be saved by) that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> who was Crucified at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> above sixteen hundred yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: whom the Quakers nullifie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl> Evill men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>Haereticas habendas est omnis ille, qui Christo quidem</hi> se credere confitetur, aliud tamen de veritate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ristiana credit, quā habeat <hi>Christianae fidei definitio.</hi>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Orig.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Haeretici o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tendant <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cornua</hi> quae sunt praetensio scripturae, innocentia, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, sed loquntur, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> docent <hi>&amp; diaco,</hi> id est, &amp; Diabolus, qui est primus Autor mendacii, &amp; falsum dogmatum. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> Edward Thomas, <hi>and are to be sold at his house in</hi> Green-Arbor. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114647:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114647:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Take this preluminary Epistle as <hi>manductive</hi> and giving some light to the ensuing Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</head>
            <p>ANY observant eye that waits upon the <hi>administrations</hi> of God, either in the world <hi>in generall,</hi> or the Church <hi>in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall,</hi> will easily discern, that he doth all things <hi>wisely,</hi> in number, weight, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; and that though there be great <hi>variety,</hi> yet all tend to <hi>unity:</hi> and so draw near unto himself, who is, <hi>The One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whoever shall observe his <hi>methodes,</hi> in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (Church or world) shall finde, that <hi>the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of his works makes its <hi>sabbath</hi> of rest and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, in the mutuall <hi>subserviency</hi> of all the <hi>parts</hi> to the common interest of the <hi>whole,</hi> as one body.</p>
            <p>And the more they act in and toward <hi>unity,</hi> the better do they answer <hi>their</hi> common end and <hi>his</hi> intention. This may be seen in those <hi>contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions</hi> of assistances, that are between the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114647:3"/>though at greater distances, as the <hi>heavens</hi> and the <hi>earth;</hi> and in the earth, <hi>one</hi> towards <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> which I need not exemplifie. If any <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend</hi> it not, I speak not to <hi>such</hi> a Reader. The same also is apparent in the <hi>lesser</hi> world of man, where variety of parts, members, and humours, make up but <hi>una,</hi> though some of them (the humours) much differing, yet modulated by an allay of <hi>temperament,</hi> promote the welfare of the <hi>whole.</hi> And that which I would further no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie is, that as they thus <hi>concenter</hi> in their <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> so in their constant <hi>uniformity;</hi> not shif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their work or station <hi>assigned</hi> them, but by the clear and assured ductures of that hand which <hi>fixed</hi> them. Its true, while these worlds were in their <hi>fieri,</hi> there was (as it were) much knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hammering (as I may say) and changing and altering from <hi>form</hi> to <hi>form:</hi> First <hi>a Chaos, rudis indigesta{que} moles:</hi> and then there was <hi>light</hi> expanded through the air <hi>at large,</hi> making day. But at last 'twas <hi>fixed</hi> in the heavenly bodies Sun, Moon, and Stars; where by a <hi>perpetuall</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, it keeps its station, as do all other creatures in their <hi>successions,</hi> according to that Law given unto them, in the <hi>first</hi> of their kind respectively. So that we look upon those who are <hi>anamolous,</hi> as wonders in nature; as <hi>departing</hi> from that fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed law and rule assigned them. So also in the <hi>Church</hi> (that <hi>mundus in mundo</hi>) is it not obvious (except to those who will wink against the <hi>Son</hi>) that the fixation and <hi>established</hi> condition of it, should be the <hi>beauty</hi> and the glory of it? and
<pb facs="tcp:114647:3"/>that after the Apostles and Evangelists (as that expanded light) had for the three first daies (as it were) of the Christian world, given light unto it, how (as the <hi>Churches</hi> were settled) they likewise planted and settled (as stars in their particular Orbs) <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> as fixed constant and <hi>abiding</hi> lights among them; to whom the care and charge of those Churches was <hi>particularly</hi> commended; between which, ours as parent and children, shepheard and sheep, rulers and ruled, there is a <hi>firm</hi> relation, inferring all the offices and duties thereunto belonging. In the faithful dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge whereof, lies the <hi>glory</hi> of the Churches, and the mutual <hi>welfare</hi> each of other. If this be not the <hi>main</hi> scope the Scripture drives at (as to Church, peace, and beauty) I know nothing. And I leave to all intelligent Readers to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine with what eye then are we to look upon, and how shall we reckon of those <hi>arrant</hi> Omniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant and extravagant undertakers, who (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no <hi>fixed</hi> station) go up and down like Gip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies; but as <hi>wandring</hi> stars and meteors, or rather as blazing <hi>comets,</hi> who commonly portend some <hi>mischief,</hi> a generation of men, of whom we find no <hi>constitution</hi> in the Scripture. The very defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and apostacy of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> though it intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd much <hi>corruptions</hi> into the Churches, yet it could not destroy Gods <hi>Order,</hi> but that he had his faithfull <hi>Antipas,</hi> his constant Martyrs and Witnesses, even where Satans throne was.</p>
            <p>But as for this generation of men (the Quakers) what are they, but Satans Factors, and bear his
<pb facs="tcp:114647:4"/>name, <hi>Apollyon</hi> and <hi>Abaddon:</hi> destroye, tearing, laying waste, confounding <hi>Ministers, Ministrie, Word, Churches,</hi> unity, order, peace, civility, good manners, yea, truth it self and all Religion. So that of all the <hi>wild Boars</hi> out of the wood, never came such <hi>spoylers</hi> into the Vineyard as these are: And now by the just hand of God upon them, in their <hi>infatuation,</hi> they are come to a high mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of <hi>blasphemy,</hi> so that one of them dares (most presumtuously) to personate our <hi>Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and (most idolatrously) to take unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, not onely the <hi>incommunicable</hi> Title of our Lord; but also to accept of <hi>divine</hi> honour and worship, the discovery whereof, is the subject of this ensuing <hi>Narrative;</hi> wherein you have the <hi>manner</hi> of their entrance into the City of <hi>Bristol,</hi> with some of their blasphemous <hi>Letters</hi> found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and their <hi>Examinations</hi> thereupon, before the Magistrates hereof, with some other intervenient and <hi>considerable</hi> passages. I have not inserted <hi>all</hi> the Letters, nor <hi>all</hi> the Examinations, because many of them were frivolous, and it would be unnecessarily tedious: But this I can and do <hi>faithfully</hi> assure you, that there is nothing here, of the one or other, but what is <hi>reall truth,</hi> as will be made good upon any occasion. One thing more I'le point you to; &amp; then I leave you to the Narrative it self: And that is; that you shall here finde the <hi>Quakers confusion,</hi> and their high, flying, bragging vants of <hi>unity;</hi> here thou shalt see <hi>James Nailer</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> their two chief Leaders and their followers, at daggers
<pb facs="tcp:114647:4"/>drawing one against another, which is a <hi>suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> discovery of that cheat of theirs, that they were all led by that one, true, and unerring, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible spirit:</hi> I shall not need say any thing here by way of caution or counsell, having done some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to that purpose in the discourse it self. And therefore <hi>commending thee good Reader, unto God and to the word of his grace, which is able to build thee up, and to give thee an inheritance among all those that are sanctified by faith in Christ Jesus: I rest ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my house in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll</hi>
                  <date>5. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the service of the common salvation,</hi> Ra. Farmer.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Reader, thou hadst had this Narrative much soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but in expectation of something further to have been added, it hath been hitherto forborn.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb facs="tcp:114647:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114647:5"/>
            <head>A True Narrative of the late Examination of <hi>Iames Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He variety and difference of <hi>faces</hi> in the world, is not more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, then the variety and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of minds. And that which may increase the wonder is, that there should be such diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and variety, in, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that, which in it self is but one, <hi>sc. Happinesse.</hi> And which, as it is in it self but one, so there is but one way to it. True it is, there is a latitude in the way; and there are many paths: So that we may not say, that every one that walketh not in the very same <hi>path</hi> with us, is out of the way. But yet withall, we must say; that although there be <hi>a latitude,</hi> yet it is not so broad; but some may (and do) go out of the way, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>by-path's</hi> of error and destruction. To see the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then who (as the Scripture testifie) were a long time left to grope in darknesse, (having no other light then that which enlightens every Nation) an to wander up and down in the imagination of their own hearts, worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>an unknown God,</hi> and seeking after what they did not comprehend: To see them (I say) differ and disagree in the matter of happinesse, and of the way to it, (as they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114647:6"/>did) is not so much to be admired. Or that the <hi>blinded and heardened Jew,</hi> should still look for another Jesus. Or that an Impostor should rise up <hi>in the darker times of Popery,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> was One who pretended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be Christ, and had wounded his hands feet and side, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Christs wounds, who was by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of those times immured or closed up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two walls and there perished, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to dy by the hands of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man. <hi>Speed</hi>'s <hi>Hist. lib. 9. cap. 9. pag. 522, 523.</hi>
               </note> wherein the Scriptures were denied to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; whereby they might have been enabled to discover such Impostors, is not so strange. But that now in <hi>this age</hi> at such a time, and in such a Nation as this is; wherein every Mechanick common Tradesman thinks himself fit (at least as he undertakes) to become a <hi>publique Teacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That now the Devill should be so simple, to set up <hi>a new Jesus:</hi> And so farr to prevail, as to perswade any to believe him to be so; to me is the <hi>wonder of wonders:</hi> And it reads us this threefold lesson, 1. That the Devill is now as diligent as ever. 2. That man (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise a rationall and understanding creature) shall easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become a <hi>Sot,</hi> a <hi>Fool,</hi> a <hi>Beast,</hi> when God leaves him. And 3. That it is a dangerous thing to forsake the <hi>received and established rule,</hi> to hearken to dreams and fancies.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But to proceed to the Narrative intended. <hi>Upon-Friday of</hi> October, <hi>1656.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe <hi>James Nailer</hi> came riding through a Village cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bedminster</hi> (a mile from the Citty of <hi>Bristoll</hi>) a young man with his hatt off leading <hi>Nailers</hi> horse, and one man before with his hatt on, through the dirty Cart way; And two men riding, with each a woman behind him, on two other horses, and one woman walking on the Causway; whereupon one <hi>George Witherley</hi> spake to them, to come in the dry upon the Causway, telling them <hi>God required no such thing at their hands.</hi> But they made no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, but sung and kept their way, and the said <hi>Witherley</hi> believes the two men were <hi>knee deep</hi> in dirt, it being very rainy and fowl weather; and in that posture they came to the Almeshouse within the liberties (but in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs) of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and then one of the women alighted, and shee and the other woman went, <hi>one on the one side of</hi> James Nailers <hi>horse, and the other on the other side.</hi> The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114647:6"/>man still leading the horse <hi>uncovered,</hi> and sung as they came along, and so came to <hi>Bristoll.</hi> The said <hi>Witherley</hi> coming a long with them. But he saith he knoweth not what they sung, but they made a <hi>humming noise.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This information was given in upon oath, by the said</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therley, <hi>before the Mayor and some other Justices of the said Citty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for their posture <hi>into</hi> and through a great part of the City; we have a like Testimony upon Oath from a Citizen of good repute and credit, and attested by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other substantiall Citizens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the said <hi>Nailer</hi> rode on horseback in at a gate called <hi>Ratclif-gate,</hi> with one <hi>bare before him,</hi> whose name is <hi>Timothy Wedloke</hi> of the County of <hi>Devon:</hi> Two women <hi>leading the said Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers horse,</hi> with the reins in their hands; one of each side, <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> wife of <hi>Thomas Simonds</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Stationer, and Sister to <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> the wife of <hi>John Stranger</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Comb-maker, who came singing, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Israell.</hi> And in this posture he rode to the high Crosse of <hi>Bristoll;</hi> and from thence to the <hi>White Hart</hi> in <hi>Broadstreet,</hi> being the<note n="*" place="margin">An Inn whereof they are Landlords.</note> House of <hi>Dennis Hollister, and Henry Row</hi> (both emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Quakers) The Magistrates being hereof informed, sent for <hi>Nailer</hi> and his Crew: But such was their sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hosanna, and holy, holy,</hi> &amp;c. and the great concourse of people, that their examination that night was not much: But were all seaven of them committed to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for your further information, you must know, that <hi>Nailer</hi> and some other of them, had been <hi>not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> released out of <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal (by what means I think not convenient to relate) and were (as they say) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for <hi>London;</hi> but must it seems come this way to <hi>play their pranks</hi> with us, of well as in other places as they past through: For at <hi>Wells</hi> and <hi>Glastenbury,</hi> his compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces strewed their <hi>garments in the way</hi> as this Impostor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114647:7"/>
                  <hi>Nailer</hi> rode along: as will appear afterward, but to proceed. The Magistrates of this City, upon their first appearance before them, commanded them to be sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: And found divers Letters and other papers about him the said <hi>Nailer</hi> and his companions; which Letters because they were the <hi>ground</hi> of their following exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (little else (if any thing) being to be had from them otherwise; I shall give in unto you, at least so <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of them, and so <hi>much</hi> of them, as were and was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to their Discovery: The rest (being stuffed with such <hi>abused Scriptures</hi> and <hi>canting language</hi> as is usual with them, and the Readers I think, are too much acquainted with) I was not willing to insert, because I would not have this Narrative to swell to <hi>too big</hi> a bulk.</p>
               <p>And first,<note place="margin">1. Letter</note> you shall have a Letter written to <hi>Nailer,</hi> by one <hi>Jane Woodcock,</hi> who <hi>Nailer</hi> affirmed to be a wife, but did not name her husband, which Letter <hi>Nailer</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth he received from her, when he was in <hi>Exceter</hi> prison.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter thus.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> thou beloved of the Lord, <hi>the Prophet of the most high God,</hi> whom the Lord brought to this great<note n="a" place="margin">Shee means <hi>London.</hi>
                        </note> City, for <hi>to judge and try the cause of his Israell,</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">Not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet but the Prophet, <hi>&amp;c. Note</hi>
                        </note> faithfull and just hast thou carried thy self in it, for thou becomest weak to the weak, and tender to the broken hearted; when we had troubled thee, in bringing our causes before thee in the <hi>day time,</hi> thou didst not think much to spend <hi>nights</hi> in the Lords service, in writing forth the cause of the innocent, to the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of poor souls out of darknesse, into his marvelous light. At other times <hi>clearing the Innocent</hi> against the opposition of adversaries. Amongst us all hast thou shewed forth thy self <hi>a faithfull labourer in the Vineyard of the Lord.</hi> Often hast thou called to us, enquiring of us who hath hired us, warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to be carefull to be with him in the work, which for my own part was a stranger to, before I saw thee, and could not read the Letter without thee. And so goes on, <hi>magifying and speaking high words of him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114647:7"/>
                     <head>The next is a Letter to him, from one <hi>Richard Fairman:</hi> which is as followeth.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>BRother,</hi> In the life which is immortall dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved; who art <hi>counted worthy</hi> to be made partaker of the everlasting riches, I am filled with joy and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing when I behold thee in the eternall unitie, where I do imbrace thee in the everlasting armes of love. O thou <hi>dear and precious servant of the Lord,</hi> how doth my soul love. I am overcome with that love that is as strong as death. O my soul is melting within me, when I beheld thy beauty and innocency, dear and precious son of <hi>Zion,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Note</note>
                        <hi>whose mother is a Virgin, and whose birth is immortall.</hi> My soul is joyned to thee forever, in a Covenant which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forgotten. Dear brother, I have been of late under great tryall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the dear humility <hi>I</hi> rest,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dorcester</hi> Goal <date>the 28. of the 6. moneth.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>thy dear Brother <hi>R. Fairman.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The third thus, Which <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> conceives to be from one <hi>Ruth Hill, at</hi> Pauls stump.</head>
                     <p>THe word of the Lord came unto me concerning thee saying, I will make <hi>him</hi> as a hedge in the way of the adulterer, and as a bar of iron on the neck of them that run swiftly; <hi>And all the wise men shall seek for him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Note</note> and when they have found him, they shall open their ears, and shall give unto him of their <hi>Gold, Frankinsence and Myrrh:</hi> But he shall not receive of <hi>them;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Which honour was done to Christ alone.</note> for they are not they, that shall abide with him, for <hi>I have given unto him the poor and simple,</hi> and such as are upright in heart. Of them shall he take freely, for they are <hi>his own forever;</hi> for I will utterly confound the wisedome of the wise, and bring to an end the consultations of the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and they shall know, that as I was the beginning, <hi>I</hi> will be the finisher of mine own work.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>R. H.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114647:8"/>
                     <head>The next I shall present you with, is a Letter written by <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Stranger,</hi> who was one of them that led his horse, <hi>and sung unto him;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Horrid Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to be spoken to any mortall creature, <hi>Note</hi>
                        </note> which Letter was sent by her to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>J. N.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IN the pure fear and power of God, my soul salutes thee; <hi>thou everlasting Son of righteousnesse and Prince of Peace.</hi> O how my soul travelleth to see <hi>thy day, which</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>did and was glad, and so shall all that are of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Abraham. O suffer me to speak what <hi>the Lord hath moved:</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">These bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemous wretches enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Lord his Spirit to their Satanical motions.</note> There is one temptation near the like unto the first, and is like the wisdome of God; but it is not, and therefore must be destroyed. Oh it defileth and hurteth the innocent, I beseech thee wait my soul travelleth to see <hi>a</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">This pure I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, is the <hi>Quakers</hi> Jesus and Christ. <hi>Note</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>pure image brought forth,</hi> and the enemy strives to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it, that he may keep me alwaies sorrowing and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver seeking, and never satisfied nor never rejoycing: But he in whom I have believed will shortly tread Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der feet; and then shalt <hi>thou and thine</hi> return to <hi>Zion</hi> with everlasting rejoycing and praises. But till then, better is the house of mourning than rejoycing, for <hi>he that was made a perfect</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">They make no more of that Christ (as they slightly call him) that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Jerusalem</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>example,</hi> when he had fasted the appointed time of his Father, was tempted to eat and to shew a miracle, to prove himself to be the Son of God; But man lives not by bread said he, and now no more by that wisedome shall he live, on which he hath long fed, as on bread,<note place="margin">obscurity.</note> and as his food hath been, so must his fast be, and then at the end temptation, to as low a thing as a stone, That if it were possible, the humility and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles would deceive the elected innocent and righteous branch of holinesse;<note place="margin">No doubt she means <hi>Nailer,</hi> according to the expressions in <hi>Jane Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks</hi> letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> but be his wills never so many, the time cometh he shall leave thee, for he is faithfull who hath promised <hi>he will not leave the throne of</hi> David <hi>without a man to sit thereon, which shall judge the poor with righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and the world with equity;</hi> This shall shortly come to passe, and then shall the vision speak and not lye. O let
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114647:8"/>innocency be thy beloved and righteousnesse thy spouse, that <hi>thy fathers lambs may</hi> rejoyce in <hi>thy pure and clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted Image of holinesse and</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">This makes him Jesus in the Quakers since and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>Reader, do thy self so much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour as to have recourse to</hi> Martha Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, thus marked</hi> Blasphemous wretch thus to wrest and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply.</note>
                        <hi>purity;</hi> which my soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth I shall see, and so in the faith rest. I am in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, wait and the power will preserve from subtilty though under never so zealous a pretence of innocent wisedome it be, yet shall <hi>the Lord not suffer his holy one to see corruption, nor his soul to lye in hell, but will cause the mountain to melt at his presence, and the little hills to bring him peace.</hi> Oh I am ready to fear as a servant, and obey as a child. If I have spoken words too<note n="b" place="margin">Yea Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. The Lord rebuke thee if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament do not.</note> high, love hath constrained me, which is as strong as Death, and with the same Spirit cover them as they are spoken with, and then shal the Spirit of <hi>David</hi> be witnessed, who refused not words though from his servants mouth if they were in the fear. I am his servant, and he my Master, whom <hi>I love and fear</hi> and I trust shall do unto the end.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>London</hi>
                           <date>the 16. day of the 7. Moneth</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Hannah Stanger.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Then ye have another Letter from the same as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.<note place="margin">Oh fearfull Blasphemer. What, the only begotten Son of God? Who can hear this without abhorrencie.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>OH thou fairest of ten thousand, thou only begotten son of God,</hi> how my heart panteth after thee, O stay me with flaggons and comfort me with wine. My welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thou art like a Roe or young Hart upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Spices, where thy beloved Spouse<note n="a" place="margin">Which is <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha Symonds</hi> whom this Trull endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, and magnifie: As after in this Letter, its also shee her self, <hi>viz. Martha Symonds</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to clear her self to him, as in her own Letter: And <hi>Nailer</hi> conses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses shee was charged to be a Witch, and a Whore.</note> hath long bin calling thee to come away: But hath been but lately heard of thee, now it lies somthing upon me, that thou minde to see her, for the Spirit and power of God is with her: <hi>And there is given to her much of excellent and innocent wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> arissen and arising in her, which will make all the honest hearted to praise the Lord alone, and no more set up self. And therefore let not my <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Master</hi> have any jealousie again of her, for shee is highly beloved of the Lord, and that shall all see, <hi>who come to know the Lord.</hi> And now he doth blesse them that blesse his, and curse
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114647:9"/>them that curse his: For <hi>this hath the Lord shewed me,</hi> that her portion is exceeding large in the Lord, and as her sorrow hath been much, so shall her joy be much more, which rejoyceth my heart to see her walk so valliantly and faithfully in the work of the Lord, in this time of so great tryall, as hath been laid upon her especially.<note n="b" place="margin">What this is will in part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> And I am,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Remember my dear love to thy Master.</hi> Thy name is no more to be called <hi>James</hi> but <hi>Jesus,</hi>
                        </salute>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Hannah Stranger.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>John Stranger.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                     <argument>
                        <p>This <hi>John Stanger,</hi> is husband to this <hi>Hannah Stanger,</hi> and this was added as a postscript by him to his wives Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as is acknowledged.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <closer/>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remember my love to those friends with thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>The 17. of the 8. Moneth.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Superscribed. <hi>This to the hands of</hi> James Nailer.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now this <hi>Hannah Stanger</hi> came from <hi>London</hi> with her husband; as also <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> and her husband, to bring down the Order for the release of <hi>Nailer and his companions</hi> out of <hi>Exeter, Symonds</hi> parting from them at <hi>Exeter</hi> and returning imediatly to <hi>London,</hi> leaving his wife with them at <hi>Exeter,</hi> from whom shee received a Letter here in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> as we shall see afterwards.</p>
               <p>And hear a little farther to what was writ before in the margin, that by <hi>James Nailers</hi> Spouse whom <hi>Hannah</hi> in her Letter so strongly pleads for, and whom she so highly and transcendently magnifies, is meant no other then her companion <hi>Martha Symonds,</hi> is plain by <hi>Nailers</hi> own answer: For being asked <hi>whether Martha Symonds were the person intended,</hi> by the name of a Spouse of whom he was desired not to be jealous, answered he never had any jealousie of her, but would say no more, which had shee not been so accounted by him, no doubt he would have denied. And <hi>Nailer</hi> (as before) being demanded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114647:9"/>what she was charged with, answered, she was charged to be a Witch, a Sorcerer, and a Whore: <hi>But he said it was not true:</hi> And indeed it was not safe for him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. And whereas <hi>Nailer</hi> had received a Letter from one <hi>Elizabeth Smith</hi> while he was in <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal, by which Letter he was advised by the said <hi>Smith,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, cast off <hi>that wicked spirit</hi> far from him; he the said <hi>Nailer</hi> in zeal to his <hi>Spouse</hi> had struck out those words out of the Letter, as he said with his own hands, because he said, <hi>those words ought not to be there.</hi> I the longer insist upon this, because this <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> we finde much blamed and cryed out upon (as one that hath spoiled their game) by <hi>George Fox</hi> that eminent Quaker in a Letter of his directed to <hi>Nailer,</hi> which Letter was wholly written by the hands of <hi>George Bishop</hi> (that precious St.) but subscribed <hi>G. F.</hi> which is as followeth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>James,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THou must bear thine own burden,<note place="margin">
                           <p>Why, how now <hi>George?</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to whom you write, tis <hi>James</hi> thy fellow Quaker, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent as thy self.</p>
                           <p>One led by the unerring spirit, what wit your Schollers say, when the Masters thus revile each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how are you infalible, &amp; how led by the Spirit of unity? Let not the Priests know this. That is <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Stranger.</hi> Obscure.</p>
                        </note> and thy company with thee, <hi>whose iniquity doth increase,</hi> and by thee not cryed against, thou hast satisfied the world, yea, their desires which they look for; <hi>And thou and thy disciples; and the world are joyned against the truth:</hi> It is manifest through your <hi>wilfulnesse</hi> and <hi>stubbornesse.</hi> And this is <hi>the word of the Lord God to thee,</hi> Martha Simonds, which is called <hi>your Mother;</hi> she bad me bow down, and said, I was Lord and King. And then <hi>my heart was rotten.</hi> And she said, <hi>she denied that that was head in me.</hi> And one of them, she had <hi>Francis Howgills</hi> mouth, and silenced him, and turned <hi>my word into a lye,</hi> and into a temptation, and she came finging in my face inventing words. And <hi>Hannah</hi> boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and said, <hi>If they were devils make them tremble.</hi> And she boasted what she would do, and cry against. Many did not expect that <hi>thou</hi> wouldst have been an <hi>incourage,</hi> of such as do cry against the power and life of truth: And <hi>have trained up a company against it;</hi> and what is that which doth fulfill the worlds prophesie and their desires; therefore consider and search thy self, <hi>if this be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114647:10"/>innocency.</hi> The light of God in ye all, I am. But this I Judge</p>
                     <trailer>For <hi>James Nailer</hi> this </trailer>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now here you see this <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> is much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by <hi>Fox,</hi> as one that disturbes the scaene, and <hi>spoils the play.</hi> I shall make more use of it afterwards; and as this <hi>Martha</hi> is thus charged by <hi>Fox,</hi> so also by others, as will appear afterwards by the deposition of one <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Perkins</hi> a prisoner for debt in <hi>New gate</hi> in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> where the said <hi>Martha</hi> was charged to her face by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beast (as bad as her self) to be a <hi>Witch,</hi> and that <hi>she had</hi> Nailer <hi>in bondage,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And truth is, it is not altogether groundlesse to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive so of her, as will appear when you have the story of her prevailings upon <hi>Nailer at the first,</hi> according to her own confession, which is thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>She being demanded by the Magistrates, why she was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a</hi> Witch? <hi>made this answer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being among the people called <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This is one part of her examination: More followes after.</note> I was moved to <hi>declare to the world,</hi> and often they would judge me exceedingly, that I was too forward to run before <hi>I</hi> was sent, and that nevertheless I loved them well, as being men of <hi>pure life,</hi> but I was moved by <hi>the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> I could not stay though they sometimes denied me, yet I was forced to go,<note place="margin">Its like she se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced some.</note> and <hi>my word did prosper;</hi> and the last service I was in was <hi>Ware</hi> and <hi>Hartford,</hi> and there I was faithfull, and then I came to <hi>London</hi> to them, and then we were all one, and when I came, I did not know what I should do further, and then I was <hi>moved of the Lord</hi> to go to <hi>James Nailer,</hi> and tell him I wanted Justice, and he being harsh to me, at length these words came to me to speak to him, which I did, and struck him down; <hi>How are the mighty men falen,</hi> I <hi>came to Jerusalem and behold a cry, and behold an oppression,</hi> which pierced <hi>and struck him down</hi> with tears from that day; and he lay from that day in exceeding sorrow for about three daies, and all that while <hi>the power arose in me,</hi> which I did not expect;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114647:10"/>seeing I knew he was in that condition: But after three daies he came to me, and confessed <hi>I had been clear in service to the Lord,</hi> and that he had wronged me, and should have done Justice, but did not do it. And then he lay at my house three daies, and then they all having a single eye looking on him as being a man <hi>upon whom the life was born up,</hi> they seeing him so changed from that raigning power that was in him,<note place="margin">She now over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him, who had overcome all that came to him. I supposed your excellent spirit could have seen it before, at least that your <hi>James,</hi> Jesus; could have discerned their spirit. The true Jesus could.</note> that <hi>had overcome all the Priests that came to him and others,</hi> Then <hi>they all concluded that I had bewitched him,</hi> when alas I was as innocent as a childe, and they (because he could not go amongst them) all set upon me, that <hi>I had bewitched him:</hi> so they came and plucked him away from me; I thought they had not had such a spirit in them, but I suffered in all, and he went away and came to <hi>Bristoll,</hi> where he was <hi>in the same manner</hi> in their meeting <hi>and did not speak,</hi> and after the meeting, they plucked me and held me, and I sang and after the meeting was ended, <hi>they plucked him in,</hi> and they all followed him, and so came into a house by the Orchard, which was about twelve weeks since, and there was then amongst them Captain <hi>Bease, Howgill, Burrow,</hi> and Captain <hi>Bishop</hi> and others, and they plucked me and the rest exceedingly &amp; used us <hi>very sorely,</hi> In so much that <hi>J. Nailer</hi> did sweat exceedingly, and we were in danger of our lives, &amp; they threw me down the stairs; and when they had their wills on him, they let me and him come to the <hi>White Hart,</hi> and there also they came and used us sorely. And then <hi>James Nailer</hi> went towards <hi>Exeter,</hi> and I to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London.</hi> Then she was asked whether at <hi>Bristoll</hi> she had not been charged with <hi>incontinency,</hi> and she reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, she <hi>bid them make it appear,</hi> and she said they did not mean carnally, a carnall harlot but a spirituall, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the truth, they have accused her for being a Witch, and for going a whoring from the Lord and his waies, but let her accusers appear <hi>she hath gone over all Israell,</hi> and now she appeareth to the Magistrates here, that can bring her accusers face to face, and being asked why she would have <hi>George Fox</hi> bow down, she saith, <hi>he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114647:11"/>having a lordly spirit,</hi> shee would have him bow down, and she saith not long since shee was <hi>sent of the Lord,</hi> to watch with Generall <hi>Desbrowes</hi> wife, in whom there is a measure of God.</p>
               <p>By this relation of her own, you may easily discern of what an <hi>active spirit</hi> this <hi>Martha</hi> is. And although I did intend not to mention it (namely the means of <hi>Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and his companions deliverance out of prison) yet now forasmuch as I conceive it may <hi>be usefull:</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to others, but to those Honourable Persons who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the enlargment of these wretched <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> as a caution for the future, not so easily to receive into their houses, and give entertainment unto such ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents; I shall lay before you the diligence of this hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife,</p>
               <p>The Wife of Major Generall <hi>Desbrow</hi> being sick (who is fince dead) this busie companion <hi>Martha Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> puts her self upon the service to attend and watch with her, for she confessed she was not sent for thither: But she said, she was <hi>moved or sent of the Lord</hi> to it (as tis the garb of these <hi>bold Deceivers</hi> to entitle the Lord, and the the spirit to all their wicked practices and suggestions) and there (it seems) by her dilligence and subtilty she so far infinuated, as that she procured the enlargement of <hi>Nailer</hi> and his Company.</p>
               <p>This I the rather mention, that those who have <hi>power in their hands</hi> may see how easily and mischievously they may become instrumentall to wicked, ungodly, and unchristian practises; for clear I am; neither is High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, nor the Maj. Generall would so easily have yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their enlargment <hi>or any way tollerated such bold blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers,</hi> could they have foreseen the issue.</p>
               <p>But I proceed in our Narrative. This notable piece <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> being (as before) so charged, sends a Letter to her beloved <hi>James</hi> (or <hi>Jesus</hi>) <hi>pleading her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency:</hi> True it is, <hi>Nailer</hi> upon his examination said, it was a coppy of a Letter from <hi>Martha Symonds,</hi> to one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114647:11"/>
                  <hi>William Dewsbury:</hi> but as I shall shew afterwards, <hi>Nailer</hi> can lie and juggle, and the very contents and language will easily declare to whom it was written, namely to <hi>Nailer</hi> himself. And it being found upon him.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter thus.</head>
                     <p>OH let me for evermore be tried <hi>by the bands of Jesus.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">In her Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. she saies she cals him Lord, and that she ought to worship him.</note> But should it enter into the heart of <hi>my Lord,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Servant of being guilty in this matter; would my life could go forever for <hi>Israell,</hi> for it is not I that troubleth it, neither am I guilty in this matter: Oh that I were before thee a little, that thou mayest try mee,<note n="a" place="margin">So that he is that Jesus by whose hand she would be tryed. As in the beginning of the Letter.</note> for I know thou canst discerne simplicity. But the time is not yet come, thought not farr off. But keep thy Temple clear, <hi>where the beauty of holinesse is,</hi> and let no thought nor jealousie enter, to cause thee to stumble innocency, for I see the Lord is arising as one comming up from the wine presse of his Fathers wrath, and he catcheth at the refuge of lies and cleares all before him, like a refiners fire, then shall all behold innocencie.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>M. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>And now here followes a Blaspemous Letter sent by <hi>Tho. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> the husband of this <hi>Martha.</hi> Now this Letter was sent by <hi>Thomas Symonds</hi> to <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal, probably as <hi>Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> call, to come out of prison.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THou King of Israell,</hi> and Son of the most high; arise, arise <hi>in thy mighty power:</hi> Shew thy self a Lyon to thy enemies, a Lamb to the innocent; make haste and come away in the beauty of holinesse, <hi>because of the sweet odour of thy oyntment powred forth, therefore do the virgins love thee,</hi> and they wait to see thy day,<note n="a" place="margin">When the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the new life shall be born in him, &amp; then be shall be Jesus. As in <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. <hi>p. 19</hi>
                        </note> and the innocent doth cry come away.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Thomas Symonds.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>From a glimmering of the day.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="examinations">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114647:12"/>
               <head>And now here I shall (I suppose fitly) give you in the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers</hi> of these wreches to some <hi>Questions</hi> proposed to them before the magistrates at their examinations, whereby you may see how these Blasphemous expressions are ownd by them.</head>
               <div type="examination">
                  <p>ANd first <hi>James Nailer</hi> of <hi>Wakefield</hi> in the County of <hi>York</hi> being asked what his name was,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nailers</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> answered that his name given him by the world was <hi>James Nailer.</hi> Quest. <hi>How he lived? Ans.</hi> Without care as the Lillies, and that he was maintained by his Father. Quest. <hi>Who is your Father? Ans.</hi> Him whom you call <hi>God.</hi> Q. <hi>What was your businesse to</hi> Bristoll? <hi>A.</hi> I came as I was guided by my Father in my way to <hi>London. Being asked upon the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of that</hi> Letter <hi>that calls him a</hi> Prophet. He answered he was a prophet of the most high God. And being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded why the title is given him of being <hi>a Judge to try the cause of Israell,</hi> he would not make answer.<note place="margin">We may guesse at his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, but his Logique is too weak.</note> As to the Letter from <hi>Hannah Stranger</hi> wherein he is stiled <hi>the only begotten Son of God,</hi> he saith he received it from her when he was in <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal. Quest. <hi>Are you the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God? Ans.</hi> I am the Son of God, <hi>and the Son of God is but one.</hi> Quest. <hi>Is your name</hi> Jesus? <hi>How long have you been termed so? Is there any other</hi> Jesus? To nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these would he answer, neither affirming or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Quest.<note place="margin">Blasphemously applyed.</note>
                     <hi>Are you</hi> the ever lasting Son of God, <hi>and King of Righteousnesse? Ans.</hi> I am the Son of God, <hi>and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting righteousnesse is wrought in mee. And if you knew the Father you would know me also.</hi> Quest. <hi>Are any of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions in the said Letter Blasphemy? Ans.</hi> That which is received of the Lord is truth. Being asked whose Letter that was signed <hi>T. S.</hi> (which is the last I have before gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you a copy of) he saith <hi>Thomas Symonds</hi> sent it to him to <hi>Exeter</hi> Goal.<note place="margin">Again blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously misap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</note> Quest. <hi>Are you the King of Israell? A:</hi> I have no Kingdome in this world, but I reigne in the Father. Quest. <hi>Are you the Lamb of God</hi> in whom the hope of Israell stands? <hi>Ans.</hi> If I were not his Lamb I should not be sought to devoured.<note place="margin">Note this Imp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ostor.</note> Quest. <hi>Are any of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114647:12"/>those expressions</hi> (as spoken to you) <hi>Blasphemy? A.</hi> Who made you a Judge over them. Q. <hi>Why came you into the Citty in such an unusuall manner.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Impostor.</note> Two women <hi>leading your borse, and singing,</hi> holy, holy, &amp;c. <hi>with one</hi> bare <hi>before you? A.</hi> It was for the praises of my Father, and I may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse any thing that is moved of the Lord; and that their Father commanded them to do. Q, <hi>Doest thou think the Father commanded them? A.</hi> Yea.<note place="margin">Here you see he owns these bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spemies,</note> Q. <hi>Whom did they mean by</hi> holy, holy, &amp;c. <hi>A.</hi> They are of age to answer for themselves. Q. <hi>When you rid through</hi> Glassenbury <hi>and</hi> Wells, <hi>did not some spread their cloathes on the ground before you? A.</hi> I believe they did. Q. <hi>Have you called</hi> Martha Symonds <hi>mother, as in</hi> George Foxes <hi>Letter? A. George Fox</hi> did lie, she was neither called Mother by him nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him. Q. <hi>Are those things that</hi> George Bishopp <hi>hath writ in that Letter</hi> (<hi>for that Letter of</hi> Foxes, <hi>(was as before) writ with</hi> George Bishopps <hi>hand</hi>) <hi>are they truth or are they a lie? A.</hi> Yea, they are a lyc. Q. <hi>Have you a Wife? A.</hi> There is a woman whom the world <hi>calleth</hi> my wife, and there are children that were mine according to the <hi>flesh.</hi> Q <hi>Those Books you have written and published do you own them stall, and are they</hi> truth? <hi>A.</hi> Yea.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="examination">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Examination of</hi> Martha Symonds <hi>the wife of</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Symonds <hi>of</hi> London <hi>Stationer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>QUestion <hi>Why did you sing before</hi> James Nailer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Martha Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. The Image is born up.</note> holy, &amp;c. <hi>When he rode into</hi> Bristoll, <hi>and led his horse? Answer</hi> I know not <hi>James Nailer. Q. Do you know there was such a one? A.</hi> He was but now is past to a more pure estate, and the power of the Lord carried me to sing and lead his horse. Q. Hannah Stranger <hi>in her Letter calls him</hi> the fairest of ten thousand the hope of Israell, the only begotten Son of God: <hi>Is</hi> James Nailer <hi>so?</hi> A. For <hi>James Nailer</hi> he is buried in mee, and have promised to come the second time. Q. <hi>Do you believe it was well to call and stile him so as in the Letter?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114647:13"/>A.</hi> I cannot judge them. Q. <hi>Why did you lead his horse and fall on your knees before him? A.</hi> In obedience to the power on high. Q. <hi>Why did you fall down and worship. him?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">So that he is worshipped by them. As after.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I ought to do it. Q. <hi>Is.</hi> James Nailor <hi>the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lasting Son of Righteousnesse? A</hi> He is the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse; and the new man wrought up in him, is the everlasting Son of Righteousnesse. And when the new life shall be borne in <hi>James Nailor,</hi> then he will be <hi>Jesus.</hi> But for the fulnes of it she doth not know its yet born up, <hi>you say</hi> James Nailer <hi>is buried? Q. What do you call him? A.</hi> I call him Lord. Q <hi>Why Lord? A.</hi> He is Lord of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and prince of peace. Q. <hi>Why King of Israell: In what sence? A.</hi> He is anointed King of Israel I. Q. <hi>By whom? A.</hi> Bya Prophet. Q. <hi>By what Prophet? A.</hi> Let that a lone, I will not answer it. Being asked whether she spread her cloathes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> She acknowledged shee did. Quest. <hi>Doth that Spirit of</hi> Jesus <hi>in</hi> Nailer <hi>enable him to be a</hi> Jesus <hi>to an other? A.</hi> I say there is a seed borna in him which I shall honour above all men. Q <hi>Your husband calls him King of Israell; Is he so? A.</hi> Then you have a double Testimony.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="examination">
                  <head>The Examination of <hi>Hannah Stranger.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>QUestion <hi>Why did you come singing before him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Examination of <hi>Hannah Stranger.</hi>
                     </note> viz. James Nailer? <hi>A.</hi> I cannot be silent if the Lord move me to it. Q. <hi>You sung to</hi> James Nailer? <hi>A.</hi> If I have transgrest any Law let me suffer. But if it be for conscience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Q. <hi>Did you write that Letter, and spread your garments at</hi> Wells, &amp;c. <hi>to honour him? A.</hi> I owne it, and intended it to him: And will maintain it with my blood. Q. <hi>Is he the prince of Peace? A.</hi> I owne him so. Q. <hi>Do you call him</hi> James Nailer <hi>or Jesus? A.</hi> I have said what his new name is. Q. <hi>Is it not Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy to call him so, or prince of peace? A.</hi> If you have any law against mee. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="examination">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114647:13"/>
                  <head>The Examination of <hi>Thomas Stranger</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Comb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker.</head>
                  <p>QUestion,<note place="margin">Examination of <hi>Thomas Stranger.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Did your wife write this Letter to</hi> James Nailer? <hi>Answer,</hi> Yea and I do own it. Q. <hi>Did you write the postscript:</hi> Thy name shall be no more <hi>James</hi> but <hi>Jesus? A.</hi> Yea, I do own it. Q. <hi>Hast thou no other Jesus? He would not Answer. Many other questions were put to him. But no answer. Onely,</hi> Isl have broken any Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="examination">
                  <head>The Examiantion of <hi>Timothy Wedlock</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> who came in bare before him.</head>
                  <p>QUestion. <hi>Is</hi> James Nailer <hi>the onely Sonn of God?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Examination of</hi> Timothy Wedlock. So that they so Sung is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by him. It was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wet wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Spouts on the Bridge (which is a narrow place) powred on his barehead so that it ran out at his knees</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> I own him to be the Sonn of God. Q. <hi>Why did you and the Women sing before him</hi> holy, holy, Lord God of Israell. <hi>A.</hi> lown the songs of <hi>Zion.</hi> Q. <hi>You will not put off your Hat to a</hi> Magistrate, <hi>and yet you came</hi> bare <hi>in a</hi> hard rain <hi>through the Town before him. A.</hi> I <hi>must</hi> do it if <hi>God</hi> command me: I did it as I was moved by the <hi>Spirit.</hi> Q. <hi>What are you in your judgement for Religion? A.</hi> I deny all judgements and opinions. <hi>Q. Why did you thus honour him in Towns, and not else-were? A.</hi> We did it as we were moved of the Lord, in <hi>Commons</hi> a swell as in <hi>Towns. Q. What made you</hi> kneel down <hi>before him? A.</hi> Truth doth.</p>
                  <p>There was not much in Examination of <hi>Samuell Cater</hi> of the Isle of <hi>Ely,</hi> and therefore I shall passe it over.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="examination">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114647:14"/>
                  <head>And now lastly you have the Examination of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas Erbury,</hi> Daughter of that <hi>William Erbury;</hi> once a Minister: who was a forerunner and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parer</hi> of the way of these Deceivers.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>QƲest.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Examination of</hi> Dorcas Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</note> Where she lived? <hi>A.</hi> With <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Thomas</hi> of <hi>Bristoll. Q.</hi> Why did you sing <hi>holy, holy, &amp;c.</hi> before <hi>James Nailer,</hi> when he rode in. <hi>A.</hi> I did not sing then; but they that did were called to it by the Lord. <hi>Q.</hi> They call'd him that rode on the Horse, <hi>the holy one of Israel,</hi> Is he so?<note place="margin">Her Answers are so full of Blasphemy I shall not note any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</note>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yea, <hi>He is so:</hi> And I will seal it <hi>with my bloud. Q.</hi> And is he the onely begotted Son of God. <hi>A. He is</hi> the onely begotten Son of God. <hi>Q.</hi> Why did you so honour him, as to pull off his Stokings, and put your cloathes under his feet? <hi>A.</hi> Because that <hi>he is the holy Lord of Israel;</hi> and is <hi>worthy</hi> of it. <hi>Q.</hi> Do you know no other Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus the onely begotten Son of God but him? <hi>A.</hi> He hath declared him to be the Son, and <hi>I know no other Saviour but him. Q.</hi> Jesus Christ was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified upon the <hi>Crosse,</hi> and how is this he? <hi>A.</hi> He is manifested in him. <hi>Q.</hi> Do you believe in <hi>James Nailer? A.</hi> Yea, I do believe in him which thou callest so. <hi>Q.</hi> Is he the onely begotten Son of God? <hi>A.</hi> Yea, <hi>he is the onely begotten Son of God. Q.</hi> What name do you give him? <hi>A.</hi> The Son of God. <hi>Q.</hi> What do you usually call him? <hi>A.</hi> I am commanded to call him <hi>Lord and Master,</hi> and I am to <hi>serve</hi> him. <hi>Q.</hi> Who commanded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114647:14"/>you to call him so? <hi>A. The Spirit of the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me,</hi> doth command me. <hi>Q.</hi> Jesus Christ is dead, <hi>Nailer</hi> is alive? <hi>A.</hi> He hath laid down his <hi>Carnall</hi> body. <hi>Q.</hi> What body is this he hath? <hi>A.</hi> That body which he hath, is by the power of the Lord. Do not the Scriptures say, I will change thy <hi>naturall</hi> body, and it shall be a <hi>Spirituall</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? <hi>Q.</hi> He hath flesh and bones, which a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> hath not. <hi>A.</hi> He hath <hi>new flesh</hi> and <hi>new bones. Q.</hi> Did he raise any from the dead, Christ hath? <hi>A.</hi> Yea, he raised <hi>me</hi> from the dead. <hi>Q.</hi> How so? <hi>A.</hi> I was dead two dayes, and he laid his hands upon my head and said, <hi>Dorcas arise.</hi> And from that day to this, I am alive. <hi>Q.</hi> Where was this done? <hi>A.</hi> In <hi>Exeter Goal. Q.</hi> Who was witness to this? <hi>A.</hi> My Mother did bear witnesse of it, she standing by. <hi>Q.</hi> If he hath such <hi>power,</hi> why doth he not open the prison doors and come forth? <hi>A.</hi> When the work of the Lord is done in the prison, the doors shall open before him. <hi>Q.</hi> Jesus Christ had Apostles and Disciples, hath he any? <hi>A.</hi> Yea. <hi>Q.</hi> Where are they? <hi>A.</hi> Some are <hi>with him,</hi> and some <hi>abroad. Q.</hi> Jesus Christ doth sit at the right hand of God, and shall Judge the world? <hi>A. Nailer</hi> shall sit <hi>at the right hand of the Father,</hi> and shall Judge the world.</p>
                  <p>By all this you see, how farre these miserable people are <hi>bewitehed</hi> and deluded, as to give and ascribe those Titles and Appellations that are due <hi>onely</hi> to Jesus Christ, to a <hi>meer man.</hi> I shall not need to aggravate the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114647:15"/>Crime; Every understanding and christian ear will <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor</hi> to hear it, and tremble at such blasphemies. I shall not therefore unnecessarily inlarge. And shall now give you the judgement and sharpe reproof of <hi>Thomas. Simonds</hi> himself, who (as I told you before) having brought down the Warrant for their enlargment; lest them there at <hi>Exeter,</hi> and went his direct way homwards to <hi>London.</hi> He it seems, having heard of their <hi>Pageantry</hi> in their way to and in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and of their successe there; writes to his wife in <hi>Bristoll</hi> Goal this following Letter,</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>HAD you stood in the wisedome and counsell of the Lord, and there waited single to have been guided by him <hi>alone,</hi> then the Lord had brought you safe to this<note n="*" place="margin">London</note> City, where he would have manifested his mighty power amongst us. Now this it was, and I know it so with you, you being all joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in love, when you wait on <hi>the Lord,</hi> there is a great power amongst you, and then when any thing arises in any particular as to speak or Act <hi>which many times arises from the earthly dark principle,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">I thought the <hi>Quakers</hi> had caid that aside.</note> to this you all joyn although you see it not, neither the life of God which is in you, answers to it. And hence comes all your <hi>Cumber</hi> and <hi>Trumpery</hi> without; which my soul was grieved to see it, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance more hath been acted amongst you since I came away, which the <hi>Lord</hi> delivered me from; whose pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence I now feel, and he was with me in my journy &amp; brought me in peace to this place, and warned me in the night at <hi>Exeter,</hi> not to return by <hi>Bristol,</hi> but to go the streight way to <hi>London;</hi> &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Martha Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</note>
                           <hi>M. S.</hi> as I was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way, I saw thee in the light, going before on
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114647:15"/>the left hand, which was towards <hi>Bristoll,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Witches walk abroad some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,</note> and my love was to thee, <hi>none else did I see,</hi> which made me think thou wastcoming along to wards <hi>London;</hi> surely thou wast the <hi>chief leader in that action.</hi> If there was such a glory amongst you; why were you not silent, and have let the people cry <hi>Hosanna.</hi> Oh how is dark night come upon the Prophets, and those who <hi>once were honourable and glorious,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>James Nailer</hi> Is it possible, can you <hi>Quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> be so decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Where is your infallible Spirit. O <hi>James</hi> where is thine excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency become, I am sorry I nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee <hi>Jesus.</hi>
                           </note> are now falen, because they were in prosperity and the Lord honcured thew, they forgot the Lord; therefore hath he darkened their understanding, <hi>and given them up to believe lies,</hi> and to do things that are not convenient, yea, I see one who was the <hi>greatest,</hi> is now a more <hi>Brutish</hi> contender than any man; and yet the friends are so blinded, they do not see it. Oh arise, arise, Lord God of life and power <hi>bring up thy people out of the dust,</hi> that shall wholly give thens, that every one may worship towards his own place.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Thomas Simond.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>Dear heart my love is to thee, and to <hi>I. N.</hi> and to <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>H. S.</hi> but this I could not but write,<note place="margin">What confusion is here, I thought they could not have been so misted. I suppose she meant the <hi>Levellers.</hi>
                              </note> to <hi>warn</hi> you that you stand single to the Lord, and not <hi>believe every spirit.</hi> Your work is soon come to an end; part of the Army that fell at <hi>Burford,</hi> was <hi>your figure.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>First of the 9. month.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Desburies wife is dead</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>John <hi>is well and remembereth his love to you. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the two pieces in the</hi> Strand.</p>
                        </postscript>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114647:16"/>
                  <p>Thus you see here, this <hi>Martha Simonds</hi> is a considerable person, For her Husband (who tis like knoweth her) tells her, <hi>she was the chief leader</hi> in this action, and gives them a hand some frump for their <hi>foolery</hi> to do that work, which they should not have done <hi>themselves,</hi> but left it unto others. Here is much matter for observation from this Letter, to evince the folly and madnesse of these <hi>pretenders.</hi> But I have an eye to that which remaines, being loath to be <hi>tedious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now I shall give you <hi>one</hi> instance more, that this <hi>James Nailer</hi> (notwithstanding their <hi>adorations</hi> of him &amp; making him their Jesus) he will <hi>deny</hi> the truth, <hi>lye,</hi> and <hi>collogue.</hi> And this from the information of <hi>Thomas Price,</hi> one of the Sherifs Yeomen of this City, given in before the Magistrates the 11. day of <hi>November.</hi> 1656. which is as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="testimony">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Thomas Price</hi> one of the Sheriffs Yeomen of the said Citty informeth,</head>
                              <p>THat on Saturday was seventh night last he being in <hi>Newgate,</hi> had a desire to see <hi>James Nailer,</hi> and accordingly went to him and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing with him, asked him if at any time <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> had bewitched or moved him to any extraordinary <hi>passion</hi> or <hi>trance,</hi> and he answered him nay. Then the Informant ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him if he were never in a trance in <hi>London,</hi> for three daies together upon the comming of <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> unto him, and his answer was nay; whereupon the Informant told him that <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> had confessed to the Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> (who questioned her for a witch) that shee once came to him the said <hi>James
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114647:16"/>Nailer,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> crying for justice; he fell into a trance, <hi>or was struck down</hi> for three daies; whereupon the said <hi>James Nailer,</hi> replied with a sturne look, <hi>did shee tell this?</hi> to which the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant told him, that shee had; and therefore he had told an untruth.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And how these people <hi>adore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Their Adoring and worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him.</note> worship and do reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this their <hi>new Jesus (James Nailer)</hi> I shall discover to you from two informations taken upon oath before the Magistrates; all which are registred.</head>
               <p>And first, you have the information of <hi>Thomas Perkins,</hi> prisoner for debt in <hi>Newgate;</hi> as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: the 11. of <hi>November,</hi> 1656.</p>
               <p>THat about Thursday last in the evening, <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas Erbury</hi> being in the Chamber with <hi>James Nailer,</hi> and departing from him to her lodging, <hi>she fell down upon the ground at the feet of the said</hi> James, and <hi>kissed his two feet,</hi> and then the said <hi>James</hi> took her by the hand and raised her up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and so departed: And the Informant saith that the same evening there came into the said room a woman of this Citty named <hi>Alice Brock,</hi> and as soon as shee came near the said <hi>James,</hi> shee fell on her knees before him, and the said <hi>James</hi> put his two hands on her head, and said to her <hi>stand fast,</hi> there is that that is pure: And then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114647:17"/>shee arose and said it was given to her to come to him for a <hi>Covering,</hi> and he told her thou art co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; and then shee told him that shee had <hi>seed</hi> by another man who had left her, but now shee <hi>loved another man</hi> who had a wife, whose wife was envious against her; but shee loved her as well as him, and then shee asked the said <hi>James Nailer</hi> whether he had any <hi>seed,</hi> and he replied yea, my seed is pure. And then came into the same room <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> and sat down, and fixed her eye on the said <hi>Alice,</hi> who presently looked upon her, and told the said <hi>Martha</hi> that shee was a <hi>Witch,</hi> and shee knew her malice, and further told the said <hi>Martha,</hi> that shee had him (meaning <hi>James Nailer</hi>) in <hi>bondage,</hi> and shee was come to redeem him. Thou shalt have him no longer, and I shall <hi>redeem</hi> him, and then shee pointed to <hi>Dorcas Erbury</hi> and said I am come to redeem thee, and thou shalt come with mee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And the other is the information of <hi>Thomas Cole</hi> under keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> taken as the former the <hi>11.</hi> of <hi>November 1656.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat whilest <hi>James Nailer, Martha Symonds, Hannah Stranger</hi> and others, were in <hi>Newgate</hi> (to wit) upon the 25. of <hi>October</hi> last or there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, the said <hi>James Nailer</hi> being together in a Room in the said prison, and the Informant cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them away to bed, at their departure they behaved themselves as followeth, <hi>(viz)</hi> The said
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114647:17"/>
                  <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> one after another <hi>kneeled down</hi> on <hi>both their knees</hi> to the said <hi>James,</hi> and laid their heads on <hi>James</hi> his knees, and he laid his hands on their heads, and making <hi>a groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing noise</hi> within himself, but the words he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood not, and then before they rose, he <hi>clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his hands on crosse</hi> a little remote over their heads, and then they rose,<note place="margin">Let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders judge and weigh these a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> and he <hi>spreading his hands</hi> they one after another departed.</p>
               <p>The practice is so grosly <hi>idolatrous</hi> and suspiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of witch-craft, that I shall not need to animadvert upon it.</p>
               <p>And now to see the diligence of these <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors</hi> and Deceivers, the more to facilitate their delusions, and to gain upon simple people, who are taken with any <hi>foppery</hi> that comes in a way new, unusuall, and extraordinary; they (these women) carried with them (and which was found about one of them) a description of our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> in respect of his person and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward feature, as it was sent to the Romane Senate, by <hi>Publius Lentulus</hi> President in <hi>Judea,</hi> under <hi>Tiberius Caesar</hi> the Romane Emperour.</p>
               <p>Which Inscription is as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114647:18"/>
               <head>In the daies of <hi>Tiberius Caesar</hi> the Emperour, as the Governours of sundry Provinces under the Senate and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> used to advertise the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of such news as chanced in divers Countries. <hi>Publius Lentulus</hi> being at that time President in <hi>Judea,</hi> wrote an Epistle to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> the words whereof were these.</head>
               <p>THere appeared in these our daies a man of great vertue named <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> who is yet living amongst us, and of the Gentiles is accepted for a <hi>Prophet of truth;</hi> but his own Disciples call him <hi>the Son of God.</hi> He raiseth the dead, and cureth all manner of diseases. A man of stature somewhat tall, and comely, with a very reverend countenance, such as the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may both <hi>love and fear;</hi> his Hair of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a philbert full ripe, and plain almost down to his ears, from the ears downwards somewat curled and more orient of colour, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving about his shoulders; in the midst of his Head goeth a <hi>seam</hi> or partition of his Hair, after the manner of the Nazarites; his Forehead very plain and smooth; his Face without spot or wrincle, <hi>beautified</hi> with a comely red; his Nose and Mouth so formed as nothing can be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; his Beard somewhat thick, agreeable in colour to the hair of his Head, not of any great length, but <hi>forked</hi> in the midst; of an innocent and mature Look; his Eyes gray, clear, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114647:18"/>quick; in reproving he is <hi>terrible,</hi> in admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>courteous</hi> and fair spoken, pleasant in speech, mixed with gravity; it cannot be remembred that any have seen him <hi>laugh,</hi> but many have seen him <hi>weep;</hi> in proportion of Body well sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and streight; his hands and armes right dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable to behold; in speaking very <hi>temperate,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest, and wise; a man for his singular Beauty surpassing the children of men.</p>
               <p>But what use (you will say) could they make of this? Why, now see to what heights of <hi>villany, vanity,</hi> and <hi>deceipt,</hi> men (left of God) may run into. This wretch <hi>James <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> being somewhat fitted for it by <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily shape,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his <hi>hair,</hi> and some other advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of <hi>nature;</hi> endeavours <hi>artificially</hi> to compose and dispose himself, asmuch (as he may) to this discription, <hi>parting</hi> the hair of his head, cutting his beard <hi>forked,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming an <hi>affected gravity,</hi> and other the like, as is there expressed. And this no doubt they make use of amongst simple clowns and silly women, who are easily drawn to believe any story that is seriously told them, as if he were the person there described,</p>
               <p>And now (not to insist upon any particular) upon the <hi>whole matter,</hi> Doth it not appear, that these Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are most horrid and <hi>abominable blasphemers, deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> from (and <hi>arrogating</hi> to themselves) the honour of our Lord Jesus Christ, God blessed for ever? We of the Reformed Churches have departed from <hi>Rome</hi> and her communion, because she hath departed from the true faith and doctrine; and for nothing <hi>more,</hi> than in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king others <hi>sharers</hi> and <hi>co-partners</hi> with our Lord Jesus in the work of Redemption and Salvation. But behold here a Generation far more impious and <hi>blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous;</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:114647:19"/>who <hi>devide</hi> the Kingdome with him: Nay, <hi>rend</hi> it from him. I need not recount their bold and daring expressions: but let me minde you of one passage in one of the Letters of that notable stickler <hi>Hannah Stranger;</hi> its the Letter dated the 16 day of the seaventh month; wherein speaking of Jesus Christ, she expresses him no other than thus: <hi>He that was made a perfect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi> Now this expression is not (in the intention of it.) obvious to <hi>every</hi> Reader: But it carries in it the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>soul</hi> of Socinianisme, <hi>Quakerisme</hi> (as I may so call it) for the Quakers doctrines are a mixture and medly of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Socinianisme, Arrianisme, Arminianisme, Ananba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptisme,</hi> and all that is nought. It is a doctrine of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> that our Lord Christ did not by his death &amp; bloud shed <hi>satisfie</hi> for our sinns, and so <hi>purch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Redemption for us; but that he was a <hi>perfect patter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> example</hi> to us of righteousnesse, holinesse, obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> suffering. To be justified by <hi>anothers</hi> righteousnesse, is with them <hi>irrationall,</hi> and therefore rejected and denied. And one egge is not more like another, than the doctrines of the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> aswell in this as in other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. The pure image of Christ must be brought forth <hi>in us,</hi> we must be perfect and free from <hi>all sinn,</hi> and then we are justified, and then we are righteous, <hi>and not till then.</hi> And if this be the doctrine that the Churches of Christ truly reformed have received; <hi>Ille renounce my share in Christianity.</hi> And yet that this is the doctrine of the Quakers, is so manifest, that he who is but in any measure (with understanding) conversant in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nanot but <hi>acknowledge</hi> it: and I suppose none of them deny it. And if thus they bear the <hi>greatest</hi> burthen inthe work of their own Redemption and Salvation no marvel if they themselvs have the greatest share of the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> of being their own <hi>Jesus:</hi> And if the <hi>thing</hi> belong to them, much more the <hi>name;</hi> and then these people have done well, and not blasphemed: All that they have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114647:19"/>said, belongs not to <hi>James Nailer onely,</hi> but to <hi>every</hi> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified person; every one is <hi>Jesus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But some will be ready to jog me by the elbow, and say, why do you upon this occasion charge these things upon the <hi>Quakers?</hi> They have <hi>renounced, denied, James Nailer</hi> and his companions; yea, so it seems by <hi>George Fox, alias Bishopp</hi>'s Letter; <hi>James</hi> thou must bear thine own Burthen, thou and thy Companie, and it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest <hi>thou</hi> and thy Disciples are <hi>joyned with the world against the truth.</hi> And your iniquity doth increase. Aye, and this is the word of the Lord to thee; So that <hi>Goorge Fox</hi> cannot revoke it; yea, and <hi>James</hi> doth nourish and train up a company against the truth, Read the Letter. Yea, most of the <hi>wisest</hi> and <hi>subtlest Quakers</hi> in the town do <hi>rail</hi> against them. Why, how now <hi>James,</hi> alias <hi>Jesus,</hi> what is beome of thy <hi>infallible Spirit,</hi> whereby your giving out of Books, and Papers, and Speakings, were from the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Eternall Spirit,</hi> as they use to say, whereby they were as true as Scriptures? What assurance can you give your Discipels <hi>now,</hi> that you have not <hi>cheated</hi> them allthis while? <hi>George Fox</hi> (as true a Prophet as thy self hath a word from the Lord, that thou art a wioked wretch, and <hi>trainest up a company</hi> of wretches against the truth. It seens that all who have spoken so highly of your excellent Majesty are <hi>lyers,</hi> and thy Spouse <hi>Martha</hi> is a very. <hi>Baggage,</hi> and <hi>Hannah Stranger</hi> is a deceitfull <hi>Trull.</hi> O. cease your singing, and weep and howl you <hi>chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Blasphemers, for there is never a <hi>Jesus</hi> among you. Oh <hi>James,</hi> Thou must no longer sit as Judge upon the bench to judge and try <hi>the cause of Israell.</hi> Come down thou Lucifer, thou Son of the morning, thou who hast been from the beginning, ever since the mistery of this iniquity of <hi>Quokers</hi> began to worke, and hast laboured to<note n="*" place="margin">Witnes his many writings and indesati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable travells like the Seribes and Pharisees, who compasse Sea and Land to make Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, though they make them the children of the devil, <hi>Mat. 23.15.</hi>
                  </note> promote it, as much as any of them all, come down and stand at the Barr, hold up thy hand; thou must be tryed. Yea, thou art already tried and weighted, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114647:20"/>art found too light, George Fox and <hi>George Bishopp</hi> who have the eternal imediate and infallible spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, have borne testimony against you, yea, they both; and <hi>John Audland</hi> and Captain <hi>Beal,</hi> and <hi>Fowgill</hi> and <hi>Burrcugh,</hi> did at <hi>James</hi> tide last, when at the end of one of one of your meetings at <hi>Bristoll,</hi> they called and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you and <hi>Martha Symonds</hi> into a house, and there beat and sorely used you, to the endangering of your lives, as <hi>Martha</hi> said upon her examination before our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates: and this testimony they bear still against you: for <hi>George</hi> saies in his Letter, you are <hi>wilfull and stubborn;</hi> and for my part I know nothing to hinder your Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. And I hope the Parliament will give Order for it. Onely this one refuge remains; That you do (and that with speed) get you some apostatized Black Coat (and such there are, though but a few) <hi>to plead your Christ-like innocency, against the cry of your high Priests;</hi> for surely they will come in against you too: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the rest, I have this Testimony against thee <hi>James</hi> (clear it as thou canst) Since <hi>James-tide</hi> last, a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this City (who owes you no ill will) was at the <hi>Bull and Mouth</hi> (your great meeting place) where you use to stand upon your infallible tripode, to speak hypocriticall lies in the name of the Lord (and there came in two men with Papers in their hands and many following them, and asked for thee <hi>James Nailer;</hi> who not appearing, they told thy disciples (there met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) where thou hadst a Bastard or a Wench with Childe; and askt them whether they would own thee? It is true one of the company stood up in thy behalf, and <hi>Commanded all flesh to be filent.</hi> And fell to recriminate those men: And so they sell to railing and reproaching (as you oft times do) so farr, as that the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man my (witnesse) was afraid they would fall to fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And so for fear of her life shee left them and came away, and hath not since borne such affection to your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114647:20"/>way as heretofore. But <hi>James,</hi> this quarrelling doth not answer the matter, nor clear your innocency, nor avoyd the sentence given out against you by <hi>George Fox,</hi> and therefore away with him. But stay, may not <hi>George Fox</hi> and <hi>George Bishopp</hi> be liers. For if we can take that off (which comes from the Lord) wee will deny this, and there is an end, let us consider a little and weigh things. And as I remember <hi>James</hi> in his examination (before set down) sayes that <hi>George Fox did lie</hi> in charging him as he doth in that letter, and that what <hi>George Bishopp</hi> had writt was <hi>a lie,</hi> and truly if those high testimonies of those in fallible Saints (before exprest) be true, <hi>James</hi> is as good, yea a better then either of the <hi>Georges, Fox</hi> or <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopp;</hi> and I could have brought other testimonies for him. Among others, <hi>Judge Fells Wife</hi> (and such discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing folkes cannot easily be mistaken) who in a Letter to <hi>James,</hi> written from <hi>Swarthmore</hi> the Eighteenth day of the Sixth Moneth; subscribes her selfe, <hi>his Sister in the Eternalls never to be forgotten.</hi> Its true in that Letter shee tells him, that shee hath heard something, which hath made her heart to <hi>ake,</hi> and shee would hear from him in particular, and then shee saith shee should be more satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. It may be shee had heard of that <hi>Bastard.</hi> However shee subscribes her self as aforesaid, and he her dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and her dear love and life is to him, and her Soul and Bowells reacheth unto him, her dearly beloved in the eternall life and unity of the Spirit; <hi>where no unclean can enter,</hi> nor he that maketh <hi>abomination,</hi> or maketh <hi>a lie.</hi> So that <hi>James</hi> is right, and for ought appears, <hi>George Fox</hi> and <hi>George Bishopp</hi> may be liers too,; yea, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>John Audland</hi> did (so please the company) joyn in abusing him at the house as before, yet since that a pretty while) he is his dear Brother; and his Soul loves him dearly. And he gives him an aceount from <hi>Bristoll</hi> how their Cause prospered at <hi>London,</hi> as appears by this following Letter, which being found about
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114647:21"/>
                  <hi>James</hi> among the rest, he upon his examination confest was from <hi>John Audland,</hi> which is thus.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>J. N.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>MY dear Brother my Soul loves thee,</hi> and <hi>dearly</hi> do I salute thee <hi>dear heart.</hi> I was lately at <hi>London</hi> and staied there about a week, and friends there are quiet and in <hi>good order</hi> as for any thing that I saw, and the <hi>work of God</hi> goes on; and here a wayes friends are well; and the <hi>truth spreads</hi> and prospers. <hi>My love is endeared unto thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Thy dear Brother <hi>J. A.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Bristoll</hi>
                           <date>the 15. of the 7. Moneth.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:114647:21"/>
               <p>Something it was, that <hi>Martha Simonds,</hi> upon her exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination said, That when they were abused (as before) that <hi>John Audland</hi> was more gentle then the rest. It was but a packt business; and I doubt not, we shall finde that <hi>Geroge Fox</hi> and <hi>James Nailer</hi> can shake hands, for all this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended difference, and both close to cozen their deluded pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selytes. And it may be, that the two baggages, <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Hanna,</hi> have <hi>bewitched James,</hi> and the Spirit left <hi>him,</hi> because he would not be ruled by the <hi>Georges:</hi> for I can tell you one of them (if not both) can <hi>pack</hi> a business: And (if need be) can procure witness to swear to the purpose (if we could now allow of swearing <hi>Truly,</hi> as heretofore of swearing <hi>Falsly:</hi>) And therefore <hi>James</hi> must repent of his <hi>Stubbornness;</hi> And the next scene that the <hi>Jesuites</hi> have plotted, must be brought upon the stage, and take place for a while, till the next be <hi>Seasonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in the mean time, there is a better testimony for <hi>James,</hi> then ever we heard of: for <hi>George,</hi> yea, and <hi>Martha Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi> who as before hath an <hi>Excellent Spirit and Power,</hi> and who struck down <hi>James</hi> for three dayes, and made him silent ever since<note n="(a)" place="margin">For <hi>Nailer</hi> doth not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie (as they call it) now.</note> and stopt <hi>Howgills</hi> mouth; she sayes that <hi>George Foxes</hi> heart was <hi>rotten,</hi> and she denied that that was <hi>head</hi> in him:<note n="(b)" place="margin">That spirit &amp; power which rules in <hi>Fox,</hi> is denied by this eminent she-Quaker.</note> and that <hi>Georges</hi> words was a lie, as in his own letter before. And <hi>James</hi> as well as <hi>George,</hi> is voted by a whole dozen of <hi>Quaking Proselytes</hi> to be Christs anointed, and a Saint, and the holy seed, a Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Minister of the <hi>Everlasting Gospel of God:</hi> Who though he be <hi>in</hi> the world, is not <hi>of</hi> the world; and whose testimony is <hi>True</hi> against the world; and whose Ministrie is <hi>Spiritual and eternal,</hi> witnessed by those <hi>Twelve,</hi> who are <hi>One</hi> with him according to their measures, in that which lives, and <hi>changes not.</hi> All this ye have (and more) in their railing Epistles to the Magistrates of this City at the end of <hi>Audlands</hi> book called <hi>The innocent delivered out of the suare;</hi> being written in answer to my book, called <hi>The great Mysteries of Godliness and ungodliness.</hi> So that <hi>James</hi> was very good, and unchangably so. I must conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114647:22"/>(for I know not which is the better;) one is as <hi>good</hi> as another, and both <hi>stark naught;</hi> a pack of cozening <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors.</hi> But pray forbear, will some say, are they <hi>Knaves,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they fall out, and differ, and disagree? what are you <hi>Priests</hi> then? do not you do so, both in doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise? are you knaves and seducers then? I answer, No: for he <hi>inter aliis</hi> is a <hi>Knave,</hi> an <hi>Impostor,</hi> and <hi>Deceiver,</hi> who pretends to speak and act in all he doth, from an <hi>immediate, unerring, and infallibleSpirit;</hi> and that affirms that what he says is <hi>as true and certain</hi> as Scripture; when 'cis <hi>neither so, nor so.</hi> Now this we do not: we pretend no other then (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to practice) to speak from the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> and while we speak according to that, we are sure we speak according to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> whose dictates they are. And we wait, and pray for our <hi>selves</hi> &amp; our <hi>People,</hi> that what the Spirit hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> he should write in our hearts; That we might find the truth sealed &amp; confirmed <hi>in us,</hi> by our confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity <hi>unto it.</hi> And blessed be our gracious Father in our <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> many of us have the witness in our selves, and in our hearers (by the means of this <hi>Ministration</hi>) that we are past from death to life. And in this, we trust in him, who hath wrought this in us, none shall make our boasting void. And therefore we deceive not the peope by pretending to stretch <hi>beyond</hi> our line and measure: we confess we may be deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and may erre; and therefore bid our hearers <hi>try and examine</hi> what we say by the Scriptures: And if we speak not according to that <hi>Rule,</hi> let them <hi>reject</hi> our sayings: we do not <hi>lyingly</hi> and <hi>hypocritically</hi> pretend to an infallibility, as you do, when 'tis manifest to all the world, that you who <hi>pretend</hi> to it are <hi>not so.</hi> For one of you (even in this very business) must be a <hi>Lyer;</hi> either <hi>James Nailer</hi> and his Crew, or <hi>George Fox</hi> and his; or else you are both notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Cheaters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now to gather up the sum of this <hi>Narrative,</hi> and to lay it briefly before you, and so to come to some conclusion: You have here <hi>(de facto)</hi> plain and horrid <hi>Blasphemie,</hi> in attributing those things and titles to a poor mortal wretch, which belong onely to the blessed God, and our dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114647:22"/>deemer: And also pure <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in giving religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship (for it is not upon a civil account they do it) and <hi>adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the same; And these things expresly avowed and owned by his followers; and not denied, but approved and accepted of by himself. You see further that <hi>Nailer</hi> is disclaimed and condemned by <hi>Fox,</hi> and other Quakers here, as they have done expresly in denying him, and railing upon him, both to his face and behinde his back. And emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>George Bishop</hi> being (as before) the <hi>Amanuensis</hi> Scribe, or Pen-man, (if not the inditer) of the Letter of disclaimer; Here then, you have the two chief <hi>Heads,</hi> and prime and principal <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of the <hi>Blashemous crew of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> at opposition (and that in no small matter) one against another; and each of them have their party, and followers. Now this quarrel and opposition, is either <hi>Real,</hi> and in good earnest, or it is <hi>packt</hi> and feigned; if the latter, then this followes, They are all of them, one and other, a company of <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>hypocritical deceivers;</hi> and then let their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded followers take notice of it: And that it may be a cheat and feigned quarrel, I shall give you my apprehensions and grounds. Time will discover whether I am mistaken yea or no.</p>
               <p>What's the quarrel? why is <hi>George</hi> so angry, as that he must now disown his <hi>first,</hi> his <hi>old</hi> and chief companion? why, Great reason; <hi>James Nailer</hi> takes upon him to be <hi>Christ,</hi> to be <hi>Jesus.</hi> Why, is this such a crime? is not this (as before) the natural and genuine issue of this opinions and principles? But further<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did not <hi>George Fox</hi> himself affirme in his book call'd <hi>Souls Errand to Damascus,</hi> page 8. line 9. &amp; 10.<note place="margin">See Irreligion of the Northern Quakers, page <hi>2</hi> at the end, and page <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>He that hath the same Spirit that raised up Jesus Christ from the dead is equal with God?</hi> and did not he avow himself to be the <hi>Christ?</hi> yea the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life?</hi> Witness <hi>Geos Bicket, Isaac Bourn.</hi> And at an Assizes at <hi>Lancaster,</hi> did not one Mr. <hi>Sawre,</hi> a Justice of Peace in that countie, and an honest gentleman, tell Judge <hi>Pulestun</hi> in the open Court, that he could produce many would witness that <hi>Fox</hi> had affirmed himself to be the <hi>Christ?</hi> The same also he said in the hearing of an honest Minister;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114647:23"/>who will be ready to testifie it, when called to it. And hath not <hi>Fox</hi> profess'd himself to be the <hi>judge of the world?</hi> as <hi>George Bicket, Adam Sands, N. Atkinson</hi> witness; yea, the <hi>eternal judge of the world,</hi> as <hi>George Bicket</hi> witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth. These things are published by one of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, among whom he lived, and where the witnesses are known. And how what hath <hi>James Nayler</hi> done, more when <hi>Fox?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely this: <hi>Nayler</hi>'s disciples openly ascribe and tender to him, and he <hi>accepts</hi> of that Divine honour, worship and reverence which they conceive is due unto him; but <hi>Foxes</hi> disciples think not <hi>Yet</hi> fit to tender, because the world (as they think) is not yet fit to bear it. And as for <hi>Nayler,</hi> he doth not recede from his old principles, for (as appears in his exa\mination) he saith, <hi>He still owns those books he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> and that they are truth. So that they are still the same, and one as <hi>Bad</hi> as the other in Judgement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their opposition is but <hi>feigned,</hi> and <hi>Fox</hi> is not <hi>really</hi> displeased with <hi>Nayler;</hi> or if he be, it may be he and his are offended that <hi>James</hi> should <hi>manifest</hi> himself to the world, to be <hi>Jasus,</hi> before him. But then thirdly, I conceive their disagreement may be but in outward semblance, for this reason; There is a rule, <hi>dignoscitur ex sovijs</hi>—When a man is a stranger, and is not known what a kinde of man he is, in respect of his qualities and manners; he may be known (and that much) by his <hi>companious.</hi> Now then, if we may judge of <hi>George Fox</hi> (whom we do not so well know here) by his <hi>Companions</hi> and their <hi>practises</hi> (even in this matter) we may well conceive their quarrel against <hi>James</hi> is not <hi>real,</hi> but <hi>feigned;</hi> for although our <hi>Quakers</hi> here, did seem <hi>publickely</hi> to disclaim him and his, by speaking and railing against them: yet <hi>secretly</hi> many of them <hi>own'd</hi> them and <hi>Cherisht</hi> them, in sending in supplies unto them in the prison, although <hi>necessaries</hi> were not (otherwise) want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them: Better then such blasphemous wretches did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve; and which <hi>necessaries Fox</hi> himself stubbornly refused, as a convenient room and bedding: But when some of their own <hi>perswasion</hi> brought them to him (as did <hi>James Wathin</hi> a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114647:23"/>quaking Apothecary and his Wife) he did accept them and not onely in this, but otherwise also, did they shew their love and affections towards them. We readily confess and acknowledge, That to succour and relieve strangers, and to visit those that are sick or in prison, are Duties that our Rule (the Scriptures) do enjoyn us. But in <hi>this</hi> case, when they are not imprisoned for <hi>righteousness sake,</hi> and for the Cause of <hi>Christ,</hi> but for horrid <hi>blasphemy</hi> against him; and for such crimes for which they seem'd to disclaim and abhor them: and when they were not <hi>distrest</hi> and <hi>destitute,</hi> then to follow them with <hi>unnecessary courtesies,</hi> is, I conceive, in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all un-biass'd men) an Argument and Discovery of too much <hi>liking</hi> and <hi>approving</hi> both of their <hi>Cause</hi> and <hi>Persons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be answered, All are not of a <hi>minde;</hi> and <hi>these</hi> who did thus, are not those who did dis-own them.</p>
               <p>Well, be it so: but then observe, They are not <hi>all</hi> led by <hi>one,</hi> and that an unerring and undeceiving Spirit: they are no more <hi>one,</hi> then the poor Priests and their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers are: and yet Imust observe this to you, That this <hi>Wathin</hi> and his Wife are no <hi>small</hi> fools amongst them. But now behold the Imposture and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postor: <hi>George Bishop,</hi> him whom they call <hi>Captain Bishop,</hi> he that was formerly of <hi>White-hall,</hi> he that was the great Agent in breaking and tearing the <hi>Lord Craven</hi>'s Estate in pieces; whom that poor wretch <hi>Faulconer,</hi> who died in prison upon Conviction (in he Upper-Bench at <hi>Westminster</hi>) of Perjury in that <hi>very</hi> Case of the <hi>Lord Craven:</hi> I say, Him whom this <hi>Faulconer,</hi> upon his Death-Bed, did lay the blame upon, (though no doubt unjustly, (as <hi>George</hi> will say) for who will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge such a horrid thing, unless truly converted?) This <hi>George Bishop</hi> being a most reverend Quaker, and hugely zealous in the Cause; having penn d a <hi>Fiery Flying-Roll,</hi> full of rayling against the <hi>Magistrates and Ministers</hi> of this City; which is a cleer Argument
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114647:24"/>of his <hi>Repentance</hi> for his former iniquities, and <hi>good services</hi> for the State; for which he deserves to be <hi>Sainted,</hi> nay, made a <hi>Martyr,</hi> by some undeserved death. This Saint <hi>George,</hi> who upon the first coming of <hi>Nayler</hi> and his Company (as aforesaid) in that blaspheming manner, did (to those who had occasion to discourse with him about it) <hi>dis-avow</hi> and <hi>disclaim</hi> them, and profest they had so done long before, even at <hi>James-tide,</hi> (as you had it formerly:) and which is testified by his and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Foxes</hi> Letter, (before specified)wherein they suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently charge him, the said <hi>Nayler,</hi> as a naughty Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; Yet see, this very <hi>George,</hi> (even honest <hi>George Bishop</hi>) writ up a Letter to some in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the behalf of <hi>blaspheming James Nayler,</hi> and his party.</p>
               <p>Good man! in his <hi>zeal</hi> and affection to these <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring</hi> Saints, he was afraid the Parliament would <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press</hi> them, if he had not <hi>interceded</hi> for them. And indeed, he is not worthy to be esteemed a Saint, who will not stand by, and <hi>own</hi> his Brethren in an hour of necessity, to stop the <hi>odium,</hi> and disgust, and clamour of the people here, which was like to rise <hi>high</hi> upon the <hi>first</hi> appearing of their blasphemous and idolatrous Practises; and which might justly have rendered their whole <hi>Cause</hi> and <hi>Party</hi> abhorred. It was but <hi>Christian Policy</hi> in <hi>Face</hi> to decry them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in <hi>Truth</hi> (as appears) their <hi>Hearts</hi> were with them.</p>
               <p>So that upon consideration of these <hi>Collusions,</hi> I do conceive, we may conclude (without any sensible er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror) That their quarrel and opposition is not <hi>real;</hi> nor are <hi>Fox</hi> and his party <hi>indeed</hi> offended with <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and his; but that it is <hi>packt</hi> and <hi>feigned:</hi> for I told you before (when I expected not this <hi>last</hi> information) the <hi>Georges</hi> (knew how to shuffle a business: and if this be so, I then leave it to every one (even their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Proselytes) to <hi>judge</hi> of them. <hi>Nay,</hi> but it is not <hi>feigned.</hi> And, <hi>Yea,</hi> we are <hi>truely</hi> angry and offended with them: for if we were not so, why should so many
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114647:24"/>of us together, (yea, and some of us doughty <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi>) so <hi>valiantly</hi> assault them, and beat them, to the endangering of their lives; and throwing good <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha Simonds</hi> (that precious Creature) down the Stairs, as we did at <hi>James-tide</hi> last, after our meeting as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said? And why else should we (the two <hi>Georges</hi>) write such a <hi>dreadful</hi> Letter of <hi>disclaimer</hi> to him? nor would our <hi>chiefest,</hi> and our most <hi>sober</hi> and <hi>discreet</hi> Quakers, go to visit them in prison. <hi>Yea,</hi> we are in <hi>good</hi> earnest, we are <hi>really</hi> divided; and we do <hi>disclaim</hi> and <hi>dis-own</hi> them.</p>
               <p>Well, be it so: But then are not all your <hi>high flying pretences</hi> (like the work of the Masons, and Brick-layers, and such-like Trades, your <hi>Fellow Work-men</hi> of old) become a <hi>Babel,</hi> a Bauble, Confusion? <hi>God was one,</hi> and <hi>Christ was one,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit was one,</hi> and <hi>Truth was one,</hi> and <hi>we all were on;</hi> say you. True, the <hi>Priests</hi> did differ and dis-agree, and were divided both in their <hi>Judgements</hi> and <hi>Practise:</hi> But <hi>we</hi> all <hi>spake,</hi> and <hi>writ,</hi> and <hi>did,</hi> from that <hi>one</hi> un-erring, infallible and undeceiving <hi>Spirit.</hi> Is not this your constant Language, and <hi>bold</hi> confident <hi>boastings?</hi> Why then, what's the matter <hi>now?</hi> How went the <hi>Spirit</hi> from <hi>James Nayler?</hi> and when was it? and how shall we know whether it be gone or <hi>no?</hi> and how shall we know whether ever he had it? or whether <hi>George Fox</hi> hath it, or ever had it? <hi>James</hi> his party (you see) plead <hi>highly</hi> for him: we never heard so much spoken or written of or for <hi>George Fox.</hi> And whom now shall we <hi>believe?</hi> Tell us, Wherein is <hi>Nayler</hi> behinde <hi>Fox?</hi> or <hi>wherein</hi> is he inferiour?</p>
               <p>Alas poor quaking Proselytes! how have <hi>you</hi> been deluded and deceived, by a <hi>pack</hi> of quaking lying <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks,</hi> who pretended to <hi>talk</hi> to you from the <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi> Spirit (as they phrase it) whereby they were <hi>all</hi> one; and <hi>now</hi> you see 'tis <hi>no</hi> such matter? Nor can you well tell which of these (your two chief <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi>) to believe, and follow after. What can you or <hi>George Fox</hi> (with any colour of reason) say to these
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114647:25"/>things? <hi>Yea,</hi> we have this to say: <hi>(viz.) James Nayler</hi> is <hi>bewitched:</hi> for so 'tis given out: and it <hi>may</hi> be so. And truely (I write it in sincerity) I am strongly inclined to believe it. For, were he <hi>not</hi> bewitched (as also his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants) it were <hi>impossible</hi> for them to be such <hi>sottish</hi> blasphemers, as they have shewed themselves in <hi>these</hi> actions, which can proceed from no <hi>other</hi> spirit then <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi> But then how doth this <hi>mend</hi> your matter? will any people in the world, that are not <hi>infatuated,</hi> and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially given up by God to believe <hi>lies;</hi> follow such for their <hi>guides</hi> and teachers (<hi>especially</hi> as infallible ones) over whom the <hi>devil</hi> may have so much power? and who can tell whether the <hi>devil</hi> hath not <hi>beguiled</hi> him all along ever since his first engagement? Though he would not bring him to his <hi>heights</hi> at first, as he did not our <hi>Saviour</hi> to the high mountain till his <hi>last</hi> assault, there to tempt him with <hi>vain-glory.</hi> But our <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> though he were <hi>tempted</hi> by the devil, yet he could not be <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> by him; because he had nothing in him. But it is <hi>not</hi> so with <hi>Nayler.</hi> And if <hi>Nayler</hi> be <hi>bewitched,</hi> how shall we be <hi>sure</hi> that <hi>Fox</hi> is not bewitched likewise, or <hi>rather,</hi> that <hi>Fox</hi> himself is not a <hi>Witch?</hi> I'll tell you what I finde written concerning <hi>him,</hi> in that book be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleaged <hi>(viz) The irreligion of the Northern Quakers;</hi> where the Author giving divers reasons, why their <hi>Quakings</hi> should be <hi>Diabolical</hi> reptures proceeding im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the power of <hi>Satan;</hi> In the 18, 19 pag. gives this as his last, and as an argument <hi>demonstrative,</hi> in these words: <hi>George Fox</hi> the <hi>ring-leader</hi> of this Sect (saith he) hath been, and is <hi>vehemently</hi> suspected to be a <hi>Sorcerer.</hi> And then goes on: The presumptions of his wickedness in <hi>this</hi> kind, are <hi>not weak.</hi> Some persons of good quality that came out of <hi>Notinghamshire</hi> to <hi>Kendal,</hi> told them of <hi>note</hi> in that town, what pranks this <hi>Fox</hi> had played, and what <hi>disturbance</hi> he had caused in that <hi>County,</hi> before he came into these more <hi>Northern</hi> parts. And withal, he <hi>credibly</hi> reported to them, a <hi>strange</hi> story of the <hi>devils</hi> discovering this <hi>Fox</hi> to be one of his <hi>vas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114647:25"/>and <hi>agents,</hi> while he was there in a certain house, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with many of his <hi>Disciples</hi> speaking to them. This accident, he said, caused many of his followers to desert both <hi>him</hi> and his wicked <hi>Way.</hi> And principally procured this <hi>Foxes</hi> apprehension and imprisonment in <hi>Notingham-Castle,</hi> till he ran away, and his keeper with him.</p>
               <p>And then he goes on, to shew <hi>how</hi> he doth <hi>bewitch</hi> people, by <hi>staring</hi> them in the face, taking them by the hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And some <hi>strange</hi> effects that followed. So that if <hi>Nayler</hi> be under the devils power, <hi>Fox</hi> is not much behinde him. Both are <hi>bold</hi> blasphemers.</p>
               <p>And thus have I finished my <hi>Narrative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now for you my sober and Christian <hi>Readers,</hi> who would neither <hi>deceive,</hi> nor be <hi>deceived;</hi> Let it not seem <hi>strange</hi> unto you, nor be you <hi>moved,</hi> That such <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors</hi> and deceivers are come out into the world. But rather, be the more confirmed in this truth; <hi>(viz)</hi> That the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are the very Dictates of the true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>God,</hi> forasmuch as they <hi>forewarn</hi> us, that such things must and shall be. That 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. is a full Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie of these <hi>times</hi> and <hi>persons;</hi> where we are foretold that <hi>There shall be false teachers who shall privily bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> (as these wretches do) <hi>and bring upon themselves swift destruction;</hi> as these will do, if they repent not: which mercy the <hi>Lord</hi> grant unto them. And that their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness should know no <hi>bounds,</hi> but that they should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from <hi>evil</hi> to <hi>worse,</hi> we are also from the same un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Spirit in the Scripture informed, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived:</hi> Nay, we are forewarned, That the <hi>delusions</hi> of Impostors shall be so <hi>strange</hi> and <hi>strong,</hi> that they shall (if it were possible) <hi>deceive the very elect,</hi> who were they not kept by the mighty <hi>power of God</hi> should be drawn away by them.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>There have (and there may again) come false Christs, and Antichrists accompanied with the workings of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,<note place="margin">2 Thes. 2.9, 10. 1 Tim. 4.1, 2.</note>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:114647:26"/>
                  <hi>with all power, and signs, and lying wonders, and with all unrighteous wayes of deceivings, who shall depart from true doctrine; and giving heed to seducing Spirits and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Devils <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyning, shall speak lyes in hypocrisie: and by good words</hi> (smooth words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,) <hi>and fair speeches,</hi> (or by speaking fair, or by speaking well, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>shall deceive the hearts of the simple,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.18.</note> those who are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent harmless Souls, who suspect or think no evil; and are not acquainted with the <hi>devices, method, and wiles of Satan.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.11.</note> And this the <hi>Lord</hi> may <hi>justly</hi> bring upon <hi>us</hi> in our times, to try a perverse and <hi>faithless</hi> Generation, who are <hi>zealous</hi> for their own ends and interests; but are <hi>not valiant for the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These wretches work no <hi>Miracles:</hi> for as for making <hi>Proselytes,</hi> and procuring <hi>Followers,</hi> (which are all the <hi>Miracles</hi> they ordinarily pretend to) besides that this <hi>cannot</hi> be a <hi>Miracle,</hi> if we speak of <hi>Miracles</hi> in the <hi>true</hi> notion of them, (as wise-men know:) I say, beside that, Deceivers and Impostors in <hi>all ages,</hi> have done such <hi>Miracles</hi> as to gain <hi>followers;</hi> witness, <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> who <hi>had a long time bewitch'd the people;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.9, 10, 11</note>
                  <hi>and to whom all, from the greatest to the least</hi> (high and low) <hi>gave heed, and followed him, as a great and high person;</hi> one accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the power, (as the <hi>Quakers</hi> speak:) wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness also, the <hi>Arian</hi> Heresie; under which, as Church-History witnesses, <hi>(Ingemuit totus Orbis) The whole World groaned:</hi> witness <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and his multitude of Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; and witness the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who made <hi>all Nations drunk with the Cup of her Fornications;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1, 2.</note> her false and idolatrous Doctrines and Practises. And in that place forequoted, although those false Teachers, teach <hi>damnable Heresies,</hi> (Heresies that bring swift destruction upon those who entertain them) <hi>yet many shall follow their pernicious ways;</hi> and by them, and by their means, the way of Truth (true Doctrine) <hi>shall be evil spoken of,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>shall be blasphemed.</hi> And therefore I say,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 11.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Be notmoved at these things; there <hi>must be Heresies</hi> (sayes the Aposle) <hi>that those
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114647:26"/>who are approved,</hi> (or tried) <hi>may appear or be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being therefore thus <hi>forewarned,</hi> let my counsel be acceptable; in as much as there shall be (and who knows how soon?) such <hi>an hour of temptation and trial that shall come upon all the world to try them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> Keep close to the word of God's Patience and his sure Testimonies, and you shall stand unmoveable: and to this purpose, take heed of <hi>formality</hi> and <hi>slightness</hi> in your profession. None are so neer and liable to <hi>Satan</hi>'s delusions,<note place="margin">2 Thes. 2.10, 11, 12.</note> as those who <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> but do not <hi>love</hi> it.</p>
               <p>Briefly therefore, <hi>Know the Truth, love the Truth,</hi> and <hi>so</hi> love it, as that you <hi>live up</hi> unto it, and be <hi>secure.</hi> And as for these <hi>present</hi> Impostures practised by these blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous <hi>Quakers,</hi> look upon it as no other then what their Opinions and Principles carry in the very Bowels of them. This is no other then what I did <hi>fore-see and fore-tell,</hi> as may appear in my Book before mentioned: To which <hi>Audland</hi> hath given some imperfect and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent <hi>Scribbles:</hi> which I could never finde my self at leisure enough (nor ever shall do) to make Reply unto.</p>
               <p>We finde the <hi>drift</hi> of their Doctrine <hi>all along</hi> to run this way, That that one single and individual Person, <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> God and Man; who was born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and crucified at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> (sixteen hundred yeers ago; and is as we believe in both natures of <hi>God and Man</hi> (the very same who <hi>rose again</hi>) ascended up into Heaven, is not <hi>he,</hi> (who by what he doth and suffered in that one <hi>numerical Body</hi> of his) that doth <hi>justifie</hi> us from our sins, and procure our acquittal with God at the <hi>last judgement;</hi> and so <hi>finally</hi> save us: But that a <hi>Jesus in us,</hi> or <hi>in our own persons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See for this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Martha Simmonds</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</note> must accomplish these things for us; as I have demonstrated in that former Discourse: and which (as I have there declared) is (no doubt) <hi>that</hi> which the <hi>Quakers</hi> have meant, whenas they did at first often say, <hi>they had something to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to the World, which it was not then fit to receive.</hi> Which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114647:27"/>now appears in this Impostor <hi>James Nayler,</hi> viz. That every one that is saved, must be their <hi>own Jesus:</hi> for this is but the product and practise of that old Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, with which <hi>James Nayler</hi> stands charged in a Book writ long since, called, <hi>The perfect Pharisee,</hi> which is this, That <hi>he that expected to be saved by him that died at</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>should be deceived.</hi> Which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple hath been since handed down by others; as by one <hi>Dring</hi> a Quaker in <hi>London,</hi> who spake to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant, and a person of credit in this City, these words following; which upon just occasion, is ready to be attested upon Oath: <hi>Art thou such a fool as to hope to be saved by that Jesus Christ that was crucified at</hi> Jerusalem <hi>sixteen hundred yeers ago?</hi> and hath been since spoken in a publick assembly of the Quakers in this City, by the Wife of <hi>Iohn Audland</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this following <hi>Affidavit,</hi> taken before the Magistrates of this City.</p>
               <p>The 23 of <hi>September,</hi> 1655. <hi>Lawrence Reymund,</hi> Servant to Mr. <hi>Walter Stephens,</hi> of <hi>Bristol,</hi> Linen-draper; aged sixteen yeers, or thereabours, deposeth, That about two Months since, he was present at a Meeting of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> where was (as he supposeth) two or three hundred people: at which time, <hi>Iohn Audlands</hi> Wife was speaking to the people; and (among other things she delivered) the Deponent did hear her say these words, <hi>viz. Whosoever doth think to be saved by that Iesus Christ that died at</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>he should be deceived:</hi> without any Qualifications or Expositions thereupon, as he remembreth. So that you see, It is not <hi>that</hi> Jesus Christ, but some <hi>other:</hi> for as for <hi>that Christ in the Flesh, with all he did, and suffered therein, he was but a Figure, and nothing but an Example,</hi> say they: which words stand charged against them in the <hi>Perfect Pharisee:</hi> and for which is quoted, the Quakers Book, called, <hi>Sauls errand to Damascus,</hi> where (as is asserted) it is expresly found; and is agreeable to that expression before of <hi>Martha Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi> in her examination.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:114647:27"/>
               <p>And now having done with this <hi>Narrative, Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Cautions,</hi> I shall crave leave to give you a few words in <hi>vindication</hi> of this City, and our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates; who, though they cannot be excused <hi>à toto,</hi> yet they may <hi>1 tanto;</hi> and that very much. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what Men are there, (Magistrates or others) that h ave not their <hi>naevi,</hi> their spots, their defects and failing? Look upon the best Kings and Governors, whose praise are in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and you shall finde, that they were <hi>men,</hi> and so were (in divers things) defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and imperfect.</p>
               <p>Our City and Government, are (we doubt not) voted and noised abroad, as <hi>much</hi> corrupted, inclined to, and favouring much these blasphemous <hi>Quakers:</hi> and we finde such apprehensions are had of us, by such as repair hither, and when we go abroad to other places. But whosoever shall but understandingly consider the state of things with us, as it was when these Wretches came <hi>first</hi> unto us, will not so much wonder at their thus nestling and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongst us: nor (did they know the Truth of things) will they finde us so much <hi>tainted</hi> as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of us.</p>
               <p>And therefore, that none may <hi>ignorantly</hi> condemn us, I shall as <hi>briefly</hi> as the business will bear (yet truly) lay the whole matter before the <hi>World.</hi> And herein I shall declare the ground, rise and occasion of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and growth of these Impostures among us. And in this I shall have the Testimony of the <hi>generality</hi> of our Inhabitants to what I shall discover, whether it be truth or falshood;and therefore it concerns me to be a faithful Relator.</p>
               <p>When this City, towards the end of the late unhappy Wars, was reduc'd to the obedience of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> a Committee was here constituted, consisting of some of the <hi>Souldiery,</hi> and some <hi>Citizens;</hi> amongst whom,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114647:28"/>one <hi>Dennis Hollister</hi> a Grocer, (who with some others, who were of the same <hi>Committee,</hi> had absented themselves from the City, whilst it was under the <hi>Kings</hi> power, and had been in some employment abroad for the <hi>Parliament</hi>) was one; a man of a <hi>proud, imperious,</hi> and <hi>domineering Spirit,</hi> (as is sufficiently known.) But the then-<hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Garison,</hi>) (who was one of the <hi>Committee</hi>) keeping a <hi>convenient distance,</hi> and <hi>maintaining</hi> a good <hi>correspondence</hi> with the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> held in a fair <hi>equipage;</hi> until such time as (divers of the <hi>Magistrates</hi> being ejected as disaffected to the <hi>Parliament</hi>) the publick affairs of the City came to be <hi>managed</hi> by <hi>other</hi> hands. And then this <hi>Hollister,</hi> and some of his adherents, (under the name and notion of the <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>well-affected</hi> Party; which, as it was used by many, was one of the greatest <hi>cheats</hi> that this Nation hath been disturbed by) began to be <hi>pragmatically</hi> busie;<note place="margin">M. H. <hi>H.</hi>
                  </note> being much encouraged by the <hi>interest</hi> and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> he had with a <hi>Major General,</hi> a person at that time <hi>eminent</hi> and of <hi>great power;</hi> as also by the <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> and <hi>assistance</hi> of <hi>George Bishop</hi> aforesaid, residing at <hi>White-hall,</hi> who was then a Man of some credit. And that which gave no small help to their ambitious <hi>ends,</hi> was, That at last, (after some succession of Governours in the Garison) the last (probably not acquainted with the Spirit of this man and his Faction) joyned with them as a <hi>Member</hi> of their <hi>Congregation;</hi> of which <hi>Congregation</hi> this <hi>Hollister</hi> was the <hi>Master:</hi> their <hi>Church</hi> (if I may so call it) going ordinarily under the name of Mr. <hi>Hollisters Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And something I shall here lay down in <hi>excuse</hi> of this Gentleman who thus joyned with them: and it shall conduce to our main business intended. At his first coming to this City to take the <hi>charge</hi> of the <hi>Garison,</hi> being a person serious in <hi>Religion,</hi> (and possibly of the <hi>separating perswasion</hi>) he found this <hi>Hollister</hi> and his <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> as the onely <hi>Church</hi> amongst us; (for indeed they had assumed and arrogated that unto themselves most
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114647:28"/>proudly and censoriously; looking upon all others <hi>as without,</hi> and <hi>scarcely Christians.</hi>) And that which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their estimation, was, They had at that time, a godly, learned, and able <hi>Preacher,</hi> and an <hi>ordained Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi> who sometimes participated with them in the Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, and every <hi>Lords day preached</hi> unto them, but had not taken the <hi>pastoral</hi> charge over them, although, to may knowledge, he was urged thereunto: affirming, that none who <hi>knew</hi> them would take the charge <hi>of</hi> them. But this was not known to every one.</p>
               <p>Now it is not much to be wondred at, that a stranger finding these people carrying the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>well-affected</hi> to the Government, (for <hi>security</hi> whereof he was sent hither) and being <hi>voted</hi> for the choice Congregation, with <hi>exclusion</hi> of all others: no wonder, I say, that he should joyne with them. But this I shall declare for his <hi>honour,</hi> That when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to this City, (from whence he had been for some space of time together absent) and finding these <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> amongst us, he disclaimed them, and denied them to speak publickly; and, as I heard, check'd Captain <hi>Beal,</hi> and also his Son-in-law, for countenancing and entertaining them.</p>
               <p>But now to proceed: this his <hi>joyning</hi> with <hi>Hollister</hi> and his <hi>Company,</hi> was no small countenance and strengthening to their party, which they improved for their factious and ambitious ends; upholding the <hi>Souldiers</hi> and the <hi>Garison,</hi> that they might uphold them: as was cleer by their practises and endeavours with the late former <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> when they were consulting in affairs of <hi>that</hi> nature, <hi>scil. dismantling</hi> several Garisons unnecessarily kept up in the Nation: Then did these men with much <hi>industry,</hi> (under the old disguise of <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>well-affected</hi> party) by Petitions (to which they put <hi>names,</hi> which the parties never <hi>owned;</hi> as they did since in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther business: which is so far from being a <hi>godly,</hi> as that it is a <hi>knavish practise</hi>) and by other ways, they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114647:29"/>aspersed the generality of the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> as <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>ill-affected:</hi> although in that particular, by the <hi>wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the right information of some, they were disappointed.</p>
               <p>But before, (by the means aforesaid) these men being inthron'd (as it were) in the Government, they carry all <hi>before</hi> them: and that they might domineer in <hi>spirituals</hi> as well as <hi>temporals,</hi> (an <hi>ingenious</hi> Person, as before, being not able to bear them) they send for a <hi>Tailer</hi> out of <hi>Wales</hi> to be their <hi>Teacher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now so high was their Empire, as that no man who was chosen a <hi>Magistrate</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> could be sure of his standing without their liking; they bearing the greatest sway in all things: the Magistrates standing but as <hi>cyphers</hi> in matters of rule and power, further then it had the stamp of their approbation.</p>
               <p>And now for matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> none must <hi>preach,</hi> but with <hi>their</hi> good liking; and if <hi>they</hi> had a minde to set up <hi>any</hi> man to preach in our Pulpits, be he what he <hi>will,</hi> for Trade or Calling, and how rotten and unsound so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever for Judgement, whether <hi>Arian, Arminian, Enthusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ast, Anabaptist, Antiscripturist,</hi> (or whatever) preach they <hi>may,</hi> yea, and <hi>shall</hi> too, do <hi>Ministers</hi> or <hi>Magistrates</hi> what they <hi>can</hi> or <hi>dare</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Instance in each of these, I shall give within my <hi>own</hi> charge and station: Mr. <hi>John Wells,</hi> now, and then of <hi>Lawrence-Jury, London,</hi> an able, godly and Orthodox Preacher, who came down to this City to visit his <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and having promised to supplyme on one <hi>Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> in the afternoon, was by them put by and hindered: but when that poor creature, <hi>William Erbury,</hi> (whose <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Daughter</hi> (the <hi>Dorcas</hi> before mentioned) are turned <hi>Quakers</hi>) was in the deepest of his <hi>aepostacy,</hi> then were the <hi>Keys</hi> of my <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>place of meeting,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be fetched out of my hands by <hi>threats</hi> and <hi>menaces,</hi> that one <hi>Morgan Lloid,</hi> (a person known well enough to be <hi>hare-brain'd</hi> and <hi>fanatick,</hi> and the said <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> (the <hi>one</hi> in the Pulpit, the <hi>other</hi> standing upon a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114647:29"/>Pew) might there <hi>abuse</hi> the people with their delusions; and this <hi>many</hi> hours together in a Winter-evening: the people <hi>going</hi> and <hi>coming,</hi> as if it had been a <hi>Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baiting.</hi> And these within, carrying themselves <hi>rudely</hi> and <hi>uncivilly,</hi> without <hi>order</hi> or <hi>decency;</hi> riding upon the <hi>Pews,</hi> to the <hi>nastifying</hi> of the place for a long time after, and to the rendring the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Preaching, base</hi> and contemptible. And when I had carried the Keys to our <hi>Magistrates,</hi> desiring their protection, and the securing of my people from lying and destructive vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: these men left no means unattempted, till they got the Keys into their <hi>possession</hi> to the purpose asoresaid, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Magistrates</hi> had promised me to the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary:</hi> but such was their power, there was no with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing them.</p>
               <p>True it is, (as I was informed) he, by whose power the Keyswere gotten from the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> promised that <hi>Erbury</hi> should not <hi>speak</hi> there: but promises were <hi>one</hi> thing, and performances <hi>another.</hi> And so <hi>impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>imperious</hi> were they, and such was their <hi>power,</hi> that before this, if they could not have their <hi>wills</hi> in a thing even <hi>scandalous</hi> and <hi>unreasonable,</hi> they threatned the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> that they would turn out a <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>Orthodox Minister</hi> out of the City, who had been <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned,</hi> and suffered much more then any of them, for his <hi>good</hi> affection to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> he differing at that time in <hi>judgement</hi> in some particulars. So that the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates</hi> (out of tenderness) were forced to yield unto them; and then these <hi>good</hi> souls were quiet.</p>
               <p>Things thus constituted and managed, what was one great <hi>business</hi> of these <hi>well-affected</hi> persons (to their <hi>own cause</hi>) but by <hi>themselves</hi> and their <hi>Teachers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hollister</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been heard to say, That <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversities,</hi> and the setled main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters were the plague of the Nation.</note> (both <hi>itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> and <hi>fixed</hi>) to cry down <hi>humane Learning, Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ordained Ministers,</hi> and their <hi>setled maintenance,</hi> as <hi>Antichristian</hi> and <hi>Babylonian?</hi> and to <hi>un-Church</hi> all our <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Congregations,</hi> as <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>reliques</hi> of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Superstition.</hi> Then began they to <hi>cut</hi> us out <hi>new Churches,</hi> according to the (<hi>their</hi> fancied) <hi>primitive</hi> pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114647:30"/>which being <hi>marr'd</hi> in the <hi>shaping,</hi> was never yet <hi>made up</hi> and put together. Then this perswasion was <hi>insinuated</hi> into the mindes of the <hi>good</hi> people (<hi>women</hi> especially) that if he that preach'd was a <hi>Scholar,</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less of <hi>their</hi> judgement) it was but the <hi>strength</hi> of parts and acquired abilities, and so but a <hi>carnal</hi> Preacher, be the <hi>matter</hi> never so <hi>solid:</hi> But if a <hi>mechanick,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered <hi>(eo nomine)</hi> upon that <hi>very</hi> account, his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was from the <hi>Spirit,</hi> although what they delivered, were the <hi>least</hi> part their own: and which, were they called to it, they were not able to <hi>maintain</hi> and justifie. By this <hi>means</hi> the <hi>ordained</hi> Preachers of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> labours, became <hi>contemptible</hi> with the meaner sort of people, who whereupon flocked to them, as <hi>seemingly</hi> more spiritual: but to be sure, as having <hi>greater</hi> counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; the power of the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> of mens prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments lying <hi>much</hi> in their hands. But as <hi>Faction</hi> never ends but in further <hi>mischief,</hi> this <hi>choice</hi> Congregation fall (divers of them) into direct <hi>Anabaptism:</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time, many of them slighted and neglected the baptizing of their children.</p>
               <p>And that you may more fully discern the <hi>aptness</hi> and disposedness of this people to <hi>novelty,</hi> and uncouth ways and opinions: I shall discover to you one of the most bold and daring <hi>attempts,</hi> that ignorance durst presume, or you have ordinarily heard of, even to set up a <hi>mock-Ordinance,</hi> a — of their own invention. Divers of their Congregation having slighted and neglected baptizing of their <hi>Infants:</hi> a great Woman among them having three of her Children <hi>unbaptized;</hi> and being discoursed withal by a discreet and understanding Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman (a neer Relation) she was so far <hi>convinced,</hi> as that she thought it her duty and her comfort to have her Children owned as in a <hi>better</hi> condition then the Children of meer Heathen: which she communicating to their learned <hi>Teacher,</hi> (for I cannot hear that he was ever called to be their <hi>Pastor,</hi> though he administred <hi>Ordinances</hi> among them) he (it's like) consulting with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114647:30"/>the reverend Congregation, to give her <hi>satisfaction,</hi> findes out this <hi>invention.</hi> Their Church being solemnly convened, the three Children are brought into the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,</hi> and something being prayed, and something <hi>spoken</hi> by one, and so by another (prayer before and after, is not much material:) The <hi>man</hi> (for I know not well what to call his Name of Office) having spoken against sprinkling of <hi>Ifants,</hi> being it may be the words of his <hi>institution</hi> to this <hi>new</hi> Ordinance) takes the Children, the one that was <hi>young</hi> into his <hi>arms;</hi> and the other two, who were able to go, by the <hi>hand;</hi> and having called them by their Names, presents them to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: And thus the good Woman trusting to her Leaders, was put off with a <hi>shadow,</hi> with a <hi>dry</hi> Ordinance, and her Children as much <hi>Heathens</hi> as before, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this Imposture.</p>
               <p>But now from this <hi>dry</hi> Baptism, they shall to <hi>dipping;</hi> and their <hi>Teacher,</hi> and a chief <hi>fellow-helper</hi> of his, are dip'd at <hi>London:</hi> which a long time they endeavoured to <hi>conceal,</hi> for what reason I know not, unless it was feared that many of their followers would <hi>forsake</hi> them, and withdraw their maintenance. But at last, after one M. <hi>Jessey</hi> (an Anabaptist Teach of <hi>London</hi>) had come down (it may be) to confirm them: then their <hi>Teacher</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>secretly dipt,</hi> becomes an <hi>open</hi> &amp; professed <hi>dipper.</hi> And now their very <hi>profession</hi> and practise engageth them to <hi>unchristen</hi> us, and all our children, and to <hi>unchurch</hi> us and all our Congregations: for indeed, if we be not <hi>true</hi> Christians, we cannot be <hi>true</hi> Churches. And how much stress, they put upon their <hi>dipping,</hi> I shall give you in the saying of their greatest Champion, M. <hi>Tombs,</hi> as I have it in a Letter from a learned and godly Minister, now living in <hi>Herefordshire;</hi> which Letter I still keep by me, for this (or the like) occasion: which was directed to me about the beginning of the yeer 1656. (for the date is occasionably torn) the words are these: Sure it is, that M. <hi>Tombs</hi> did never so violently urge <hi>Rebaptization</hi> as of late: which Ordinance (pardon the words) he makes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114647:31"/>of so great <hi>necessity,</hi> that all those who refuse to come under it, he <hi>openly</hi> stiles the <hi>children of the Devil;</hi> and wonders upon what ground they can call God <hi>Father:</hi> and I hence <hi>wonder</hi> upon what ground their <hi>Anabaptist</hi>-Teacher here, can administer the Ordinance of the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> to those, who (not being dip'd) are no <hi>Christians,</hi> but the <hi>Devils</hi> Children. And if he shall say, This is not <hi>his</hi> judgement (for then it would lessen his <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution,</hi> which is a feeling Argument:) I ask, By what Authority doth he make a <hi>single</hi> Judgement to himself, <hi>contrary</hi> to their received Tenents? For I appeal to all who know any thing in this matter, whether it be not the <hi>common</hi> Opinion and Judgement of those of that way, to deny both our <hi>Baptism</hi> and <hi>Ministery,</hi> as from <hi>Antichrist?</hi> And why do they deny to hold Communion with us in the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> which were instituted and alwayes held, as the <hi>Badges</hi> and <hi>Pledges</hi> of <hi>Christian Communion</hi> and Fellowship? Nay, so much do they abominate Communion with us, as that their <hi>Mid-wives</hi> and <hi>Nurses</hi> (who by the duty of their place are to attend upon the occasions of the Ordinance of Baptism) do <hi>withdraw</hi> from the presence when the Ordinance is administred to <hi>Infants.</hi> And what meant he himself, when (in his publick Lecture) he ask'd what we had in our publick Congregations, but <hi>dry breasts;</hi> and what we had from <hi>Antichrist,</hi> when we were <hi>six or eight dayes old?</hi> Which, what can he mean but <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism?</hi> This I have from one that heard him, and was ready to make Oath on't. And how then dares he to administer the <hi>Supper</hi> to an <hi>unbaptized</hi> and <hi>Antichristian</hi> person? Something 'tis, the profest, and thorow-<hi>pac'd Anabaptists</hi> leave him, and will not joyn with him but have their <hi>separated,</hi> out of his <hi>separated</hi> Congregation: they are true to their Principles, and do not juggle; and therein shew themselves more ingenuous.</p>
               <p>And here I must crave leave to step out of my way, and to say a little by way of defence and <hi>apology</hi> for this my plain dealing: I am very apprehensive, That what I have
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114647:31"/>here laid forth, will raise, the <hi>spleen</hi> of some persons, and that they will put forth their <hi>stings</hi> of sharp <hi>censures:</hi> for whoever shall put his finger upon a <hi>sore,</hi> must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>wincing</hi> and kicking. And the common <hi>blinde,</hi> (whereby <hi>ignorant</hi> people are mis-led, and <hi>guilty</hi> persons shelter themselves under) will be now practised toward me, <hi>viz.</hi> This, will they say, is <hi>bitterness</hi> and <hi>passion,</hi> and contrary to that brotherly <hi>love</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> that ought to be in one towards another; and though we differ in <hi>judgement,</hi> we should not in <hi>affection,</hi> &amp;c. You should rather by love <hi>heal</hi> the wound, then by opposition make it <hi>wider.</hi> I confess the words are very good, and <hi>smooth,</hi> and plausible: But first, Doth this any way <hi>hinder,</hi> but that when a man is to discover the <hi>grounds,</hi> and <hi>rise,</hi> and <hi>growth</hi> of some <hi>eminent</hi> mischief, (that so Truth and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency might be <hi>vindicated,</hi> and the like mischiefs for the future to be avoided) doth this hinder one from dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the plain and naked Truth concerning such <hi>persons</hi> and their <hi>wayes,</hi> who have promoted that evil? If what I have said, and shall say<note n="(a)" place="margin">What I have said, is but in order to what follows.</note>, be not Truth, let them smite me, and I will lie down under the reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. But secondly, I have observed <hi>this,</hi> many yeers, as a subtile piece of policy in the deceivers of this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: That when they promore their designs of destroying the Truth, to the provocation of the <hi>zeal</hi> of true Christians; then, to avoid those <hi>sharp reproofs</hi> which are due unto them, they'll call for <hi>moderation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Titus 1.13.</note> Which is as much, as if they should stroke us and mooth us with good <hi>words,</hi> that they might get up &amp; <hi>ride</hi> us, or <hi>strike</hi> and <hi>wound us</hi> and the <hi>Truth,</hi> and intreat us to say nothing. But thirdly, As for these <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> I'll make my appeal to <hi>all</hi> the world (except themselves) who are they that break the bond of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> and <hi>moderation,</hi> and brotherly <hi>communion,</hi> they or we? It's well express'd of one, That Schism is <hi>properly</hi> against Christian <hi>love.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Marshal.</note> And is not this against Christian <hi>love,</hi> and so <hi>Schism</hi> (or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more) which rends and tears whole Churches from the <hi>communion</hi> of Christ's Body? Are they not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114647:32"/>Schismaticks, who confine all Christ's Members, within the Chanels and bounds of their narrow Society; like the <hi>Donatists</hi> of old, thrusting out all others as the <hi>brats</hi> of <hi>Babylon?</hi> for what are we other, if our <hi>Ministers, Baptism, Congregations,</hi> be <hi>Antichristian?</hi> Suppose we would hold communion with them, will they hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Fyrmyn.</note> I never heard, (sayes one) that we have denied communion with them in Ordinances; but to be sure, they (the Anabaptists) have denied com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us, and cast us off with highest <hi>scorn.</hi> And sure I am, they account <hi>baptism</hi> as polluted: for what else means the practise aforesaid, of those of their perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to withdraw from the presence while the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is administred, as if it were a pestilential and contagious thing? And therefore, as one said in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther case, <hi>Quid verba audio, cum facta video?</hi> What mean you to speak of love, when we see such actions? nay, what speak you of love to us, when we see both your words and actions so contrary? (you may as well say to us (as one languages it) thus: <hi>Though we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in judgement from you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Fyrmyn</hi> in his notes on M. <hi>Marshals</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the power of the civil Magistrate in matters of Religion.</note>
                  <hi>and break our union with you, manifesting it openly, by casting off communion with you; yet you must be united to us: though we call your Priests Blackcoats and Antichristians, and so your Churches; yet you must not differ in affection.</hi> But (as he sayes there) this Schismatical Spirit is intolerable. And as Mr. <hi>Marshal</hi> observes (in another Sermon concerning unity) erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons (and he speaks it of the Anabaptists) <hi>are ordinarily proud, and must have all mens sheaves bow down to theirs; who will close onely with teachers and compauies according to their own lusts,</hi> pag. 30. of that Sermon. It would well suit their <hi>ends,</hi> (which is to <hi>break all our Churches</hi> to make up their own) if we should sit still, and (like <hi>Issachers</hi> Asses) couch down under every <hi>burden</hi> (with silence) which they please to impose upon us: but in so doing (and so will all those who do so) we should prove <hi>traytors</hi> to the <hi>truth,</hi> and to <hi>our Lord and Master.</hi> And to our people in general, I say thus much: It is a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114647:32"/>
                  <hi>great</hi> Argument of their <hi>great</hi> ignorance, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>all this while</hi> discern between <hi>soft</hi> and <hi>smooth words,</hi> and <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>cutting Doctrines;</hi> and that they should be so <hi>simple,</hi> to countenance <hi>those,</hi> who un-church, un-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten <hi>them,</hi> their <hi>children,</hi> and their <hi>forefathers.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whilst we speak the words of <hi>truth</hi> with soberness, let them <hi>cease</hi> to charge us with the breach of <hi>charity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And whereas some think they own our <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery,</hi> because they <hi>hear</hi> some of us: Alas, this is but a <hi>Blinde:</hi> for <hi>so sar</hi> a <hi>Pagan</hi> may hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us, &amp; we may hold with them: and <hi>so,</hi> own one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, if <hi>this</hi> be owning.</note> which (upon the ground aforesaid) we must lay at their doors. And if I <hi>wrongfully</hi> charge them, let them but acknowledge our Ministery, Churches and Ordinances to be according to Christ's <hi>institution;</hi> nay, that they are but <hi>such,</hi> as with whom they will hold <hi>communion:</hi> and I will write a <hi>Retractation.</hi> If not, they must give us <hi>leave</hi> (or we will take it) to be <hi>sensible</hi> of the wrong they do us.</p>
               <p>And therefore now to proceed upon that from whence we have <hi>digressed.</hi> While things were with us in that posture (as aforesaid) in steps that <hi>Little thing</hi> into the world, which some would call a <hi>Convention</hi> (but I think a <hi>Conventicle</hi>) of Parliament: And thereof, this <hi>Denis Hollister</hi> (so great a man was he in this world) was a Member. From <hi>whom,</hi> and which <hi>Assembly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Being also made a member in the Committees of highest concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; insomuch that it was giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en out by some, he was the <hi>third man</hi> in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this party had great expectation: As well they might, considering the <hi>Constitution;</hi> but that, by God's goodness, there were some discreet and <hi>sober</hi> persons, and good Patriots among them; who happily helped to their <hi>speedy</hi> dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As if they had been created on purpose, to come up to the House, and <hi>see</hi> it, to be <hi>kick'd</hi> out, and <hi>laugh'd</hi> at. This so raised the <hi>indignation</hi> of this fellow <hi>(Holli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster)</hi> and his <hi>company,</hi> as that he and his <hi>Teacher,</hi> (with their Society) neglected the <hi>Declarations,</hi> and solemn ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of publike Meetings for duties recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his <hi>Highness</hi> to the Nation, for a long time after: Yet still keeping up their interest with the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that <hi>now</hi> they might keep up theirs. To which those Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Garison who originally were men of an <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> extraction, and of <hi>mean</hi> fortune (and finding this City a <hi>sweet</hi> harbour for them upon <hi>many</hi> considerations)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114647:33"/>were very ready to joyn in. Raising often <hi>contests</hi> and debates with the Magistrates and Citizens upon <hi>several</hi> occasions; whom still they endeavoured (together with these men) to represent as <hi>disaffected,</hi> and as persons not to be <hi>trusted</hi> with the Government.</p>
               <p>During this <hi>distracted,</hi> broken and <hi>divided</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in come some of these wretched <hi>Quakers</hi> from the <hi>North</hi> amongst us; who by their <hi>Lyes, Monkish</hi> profession, reproaching our <hi>Ministery,</hi> sufficiently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (by the endeavours of the former) despised and contemned; and crying down <hi>Tythes:</hi> so far prevailed with some <hi>proselytes,</hi> as to <hi>disturb</hi> our Congregations: In that <hi>manner,</hi> and by those means, with which the world is too well acquainted; and therefore I need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. And now (see the end of <hi>pride,</hi> faction, discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and <hi>affected</hi> singularity) to these <hi>Hollister</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Who was then outed at <hi>White Hall.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> (and divers of <hi>that</hi> party with them) joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Also, Captain <hi>Watson</hi> and Captain <hi>Beal,</hi> who had then chief command of the Garison in the absence of the <hi>Governour;</hi> (the one residing in the <hi>Castle,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>great Fort</hi>) and these become their <hi>proselytes.</hi> The insolent <hi>disturbances</hi> of this people growing higher and higher, incens'd the spirit of the inhabitants, to see their <hi>Ministers</hi> so abused. And the <hi>Magistrates</hi> fearing what it might come unto (as well they might) convented two of their <hi>Talkers</hi> before them: who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard them, and perceiving their <hi>folly,</hi> commanded them to depart the City; threatning otherwise to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prison</hi> them. But these men, who had learn'd to <hi>despise</hi> Government, they and their followers go and come at their <hi>pleasure:</hi> And those of our <hi>own</hi> Town, who had learn'd the <hi>same</hi> lesson, give them entertainment in their houses. And by this means, provocations and distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances go on <hi>further</hi> and further. And they keeping their Meetings in divers houses in the <hi>heart</hi> of the City. And although the Magistrates imprisoned <hi>divers,</hi> who disturbed our <hi>publike</hi> Meetings; yet such was their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in the <hi>prison,</hi> by the <hi>visits,</hi> and sending in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114647:33"/>plenty of the best provision, by their Fellow <hi>Quakers;</hi> as that it was better for them there then when at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; The Disturbers being persons of mean condition, which was something observable, that they being all <hi>acted</hi> (as they say) by <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>same</hi> Spirit, it should move the <hi>small ones,</hi> and not the <hi>great ones.</hi> And so in their <hi>quakings</hi> and <hi>spewings,</hi> &amp;c. which (I wonder why they have <hi>conjur'd</hi> down that Spirit) is <hi>now</hi> quite out of <hi>fashion.</hi> Still their <hi>Quakings</hi> and <hi>Disturbances</hi> increase, by the coming of more and more Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. But they not <hi>begging,</hi> and being lodged in <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> houses, the Magistrates knew not how to deal with them as <hi>vagrants,</hi> as they deserved. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, they were discouraged and dis-heartned by some, who should have had the wit (or honesty) to give them <hi>better</hi> counsel.</p>
               <p>It's true, there came forth a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> which we thought had been to have suppress'd them: but so sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were we, we could not understand the <hi>meaning</hi> on't; and so were still without remedy. At length, their Assemblies grew so great, that ordinary houses would not receive them: and therefore they had their Meetings in the Castle, by the countenance and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Captain <hi>Watson</hi> and his Wife, (who was seen at the Bull and Mouth, at that Meeting, when <hi>Nayler</hi> was charged with a Bastard, as aforesaid) and in the <hi>Fort</hi> by the countenance and company of Captain <hi>Beal,</hi> both <hi>Sabbath-dayes,</hi> and others: whither many hundred re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorted out of City and Country.</p>
               <p>These Ring-leaders walking up and down the City at their pleasure, without <hi>respect</hi> or <hi>fear</hi> of the <hi>Magistrates;</hi> and making their <hi>excursions</hi> out to the <hi>Neighbour-Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> there to seduce the Country.</p>
               <p>True it is, These things so raised and exasperated the mindes of some of the <hi>Youth</hi> of the City; some of whom having heard them deliver <hi>unsound</hi> Opinions, to the <hi>impoysoning</hi> of the people: and conceiving them punishable by the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> did seise upon them, one
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114647:34"/>week-day, as they were going towards a Quaking-Meeting in the Country; and with strong hand endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to bring them before the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and to require <hi>Justice</hi> on them. But the <hi>Magistrates</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at the <hi>Tolsey</hi> (their usual place of meeting) they let them go without harming them.</p>
               <p>But so great was the <hi>zeal</hi> of these <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and their Abettors, for these deluding and blaspheming <hi>Quakers,</hi> that the next day they came to the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> with great <hi>Complaints</hi> and <hi>Out-cryes</hi> against the <hi>Apprentices,</hi> as <hi>Riotors:</hi> with high words requiring punishment upon them, in the behalf of these <hi>Deceivers;</hi> who came and continued here with the <hi>affront</hi> of Justice. The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates,</hi> that they might not (in the least) give coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to any thing that carried the face of Tumult or Riot, send for some of the <hi>Apprentices</hi> before them; which the rest perceiving, come up into the middle of the City to a great number, (but without <hi>Weapo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> or <hi>Staves,</hi> wholly <hi>unarmed</hi>) declaring <hi>indeed</hi> this Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: That if one of them were <hi>committed</hi> upon that occasion) they would <hi>all</hi> go to Prison. But so high, impetuous and violent were these <hi>Quakers Proselytes,</hi> that they armed their <hi>Souldiers,</hi> with <hi>Swords</hi> and <hi>Muskets,</hi> and brought them up into the <hi>midst</hi> of the City, against the People and <hi>Apprentices,</hi> and set the City into an <hi>uproar,</hi> and very neer to <hi>blood</hi> and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. But by God's <hi>blessing</hi> (upon the <hi>discretion</hi> of the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and the <hi>mediation</hi> of some sober per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons) the <hi>Apprentices</hi> were <hi>dismiss'd,</hi> and the Tumult ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased.</p>
               <p>And as we never knew the like <hi>before,</hi> so we have not, and trust in God's goodness we never <hi>shall</hi> see the like again, here in this City; although we have no <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> immediately over us: but yet still the cause of these <hi>Quakers</hi> must be <hi>upheld, countenanced, maintained</hi> and <hi>propagated</hi> amongst us and our Neighbours, by the strength and power of these <hi>Souldiers:</hi> For when the <hi>Deceivers</hi> have a minde to go abroad into the <hi>Country</hi> to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114647:34"/>spread their <hi>lyes</hi> and delusion; the <hi>Souldiers</hi> (who were not placed here for that purpose, much less, to raise Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults) must <hi>guard</hi> them through the City, as they did the very next day after; which countenance the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> could not finde, though we were often abused in our Congregations.</p>
               <p>By this means, these Impostors were so <hi>setled</hi> and <hi>rooted</hi> among us, that until by <hi>time</hi> and good <hi>counsel,</hi> their foolish, absurd, and blasphemous Opinions be grub'd up, we cannot expect wholly to be freed from them. But in the mean time, it is our hope and <hi>prayer,</hi> That the <hi>Lord</hi> will so stir up the <hi>zeal</hi> of our Governours for our <hi>Lord Christ</hi> and his <hi>Gospel,</hi> as that these bold Blasphemers shall receive such a <hi>guerdon</hi> for these their <hi>horrid</hi> and unchristian practises; as that all three Nations under his Highness Government, <hi>shall hear, and fear, and do no more so wickedly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus I have given you, an account of the state of Affairs with us; wherein I have not been exact to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the order, or circumstance of time in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: for I intended not an exact Diary: but I have been careful to give in the substance, in Truth and in reality.</p>
               <p>And by it I hope it appears to the World, that our City and Government is not altogether to be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but much to be excused, and indeed as much pitied. And now that the World abroad may not look upon us as <hi>wholly</hi> tainted with this sowre leaven of wickedness; and so fit to be <hi>cast out,</hi> or unworthy of Christian Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety: let them know, that by God's goodness (except one) there is none of those, who are or were thought fit or worthy to bear a share in the Government here, that are led away by, or inclined to these wicked persons: nor are there many any way considerable, that adhere unto them; and those who are so, (as we all conclude, who have knowledge of them) such, and their relations and adherents, as upon <hi>faction, discontent,</hi> and <hi>dis-affected humour,</hi> have been seduced by them. And that the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114647:35"/>World may know, what <hi>door</hi> they went out at; let them take notice, and it is a thing to be observed, That the <hi>most</hi> (if not <hi>all</hi>) of those, who (among us) have turned aside to these wayes of wickedness, are such as <hi>first</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sook and departed from their established and <hi>lawfully</hi> called and constituted Ministers, to run after the ignorant fancies of Mechanical undertakers, by whom, unsound and unsetling Doctrines have been vented; and bold, ignorant, and presumptuous undertakings practised, as hath been in part demonstrated. And for the Truth of this, I appeal to the whole City in general. And it is a thing the more to be weighed and considered, for that the same observation (or much to the same purpose) is made by another hand in a Discourse very lately publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which (because they have much weight) I will give you in his own words:<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitas pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bis by one C. Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. sold at the thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Lions in Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</note> Think sadly, whether those manifold revolts that have been made from your separate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations to <hi>monstrous Opinions,</hi> and <hi>unclean conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> have not been the righteous judgement of God upon you, for your too high <hi>valwation</hi> of your selves, and uncharitable <hi>separations</hi> from others: whereby you have deprived such poor creatures as we,<note place="margin">He speaks it to ordinary (but more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily inabled) Christians.</note> of those brotherly helps and encouragements, which by your eminent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, God had enabled you to <hi>yield;</hi> and by his providence, put <hi>oportunities</hi> into your hands to afford un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. What construction you make of these passages of providence, we know not: but truly to us (the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant) they appear strange and formidable: That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you fish with so great a Mash, that scarce one of a hundred are by you taken, and admitted into your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; that out of this hundredth part of yours, more should be found <hi>revolting</hi> to desperate opinions, then of the ninety nine parts by you deserted, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to us <hi>strange</hi> and wonderful; and such as we think may <hi>rationally</hi> put you upon a just suspition, and serious examination of that <hi>Way,</hi> from which there is so <hi>easie</hi> a transition, to many dreadful delusions; and through which, so many have <hi>already</hi> passed into the Camp of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114647:35"/>enemy. Thus far he. And were it not too much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side my intention and undertaking at this time, I could upon <hi>experience</hi> and observation give account of many things, whence this proceedeth. One thing onely I will minde them of: And indeed, which is a <hi>fruitful</hi> parent of many illegitimate births: And is the practice of <hi>some</hi> Congregations, I hope not of <hi>all.</hi> Which is, that if any of their Members have gotten the <hi>facility</hi> (though not the faculty) and <hi>confidence</hi> of speaking, they will gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him (or he may take) a <hi>freedom</hi> to go forth as a <hi>publike</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, without any previous examination, or due Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if any company of people, how <hi>incompetent</hi> so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to make trial or judgement of him (if they but call themselvs a <hi>Church</hi>) call such a one to be their Pastor, this shall be a <hi>sufficient</hi> investiture into the Ministery: Especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if some of their <hi>own</hi> quality, calling, and perswasion, shall but joyn with them, in setting a day apart for Prayer and Fasting, at their <hi>sending</hi> forth, or <hi>first</hi> entrance: As if <hi>that</hi> would put ability into them, which otherwise they had not: And without which (though they may be able to <hi>deliver</hi> a Sermon) they are not fit to be <hi>publike</hi> Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And for the partiality of their <hi>Ordainers</hi> (if I may so call <hi>them,</hi> who take up that work without a <hi>call</hi>) or if they had <hi>any</hi> Ordainers at all) or who ever gave such men a <hi>mission</hi> or Commission) can any man in the world, either with shew of <hi>reason,</hi> or authority from the <hi>Word,</hi> give his vote for such a man, as fit for the Ministerial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who neither <hi>ordinarily,</hi> nor <hi>extraordinarily,</hi> is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with any other then his <hi>mother</hi>-Tongue: nor that <hi>neither</hi> perfectly: As possibly not being able to <hi>write</hi> (though he may <hi>speak</hi>) either sense or true English; but as he takes it out of other mens writings? And yet <hi>many</hi> such have we had in this present generation: And who (through their ignorance) have been the authors, fautors or fomentors of many wretched opinions.</p>
               <p>It was a <hi>taunt,</hi> and a word of reproach to the <hi>Mass-Priests,</hi> and Reading Priests of old; <hi>An ignorant Sir-John,</hi> and <hi>Sir John Lack Latine.</hi> But now, by I know not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114647:36"/>what strange and fatal kinde of <hi>constellation</hi> that cuimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateth in our Horizon, <hi>Ignorance</hi> is enthron'd, and hath got the <hi>Doctors</hi> Chair: And we walk, not onely <hi>retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade,</hi> but <hi>antigrade</hi> to all the world. And whereas the Wise-men of the <hi>East</hi> were guided to Christ by a <hi>Star</hi> in the heavens; our Wise-men of the <hi>West</hi> must be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by a <hi>Glo-worm,</hi> or some <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> from the earth. As if the high-way to <hi>knowledge,</hi> were to be <hi>unlettered;</hi> and to be <hi>learned,</hi> were to be <hi>profane,</hi> and destitute of saving knowledge. But my dear Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, If you intend not to gratifie <hi>Rome,</hi> to drive away <hi>Religion,</hi> and ruine <hi>England,</hi> take heed how you <hi>foster</hi> these delusions. It's the saying of our Romane adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, that <hi>Ignorance is the mother of Devotion:</hi> But we finde it the mother of Errour, Heresie, and Blasphemy: Onely with this difference; That in our licentious ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, it hath gotten <hi>impudence</hi> and impunity for her <hi>supporters.</hi> And our people are again <hi>cheated</hi> into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout <hi>simplicity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, but there is one thing that is <hi>instar omnium,</hi> and puts all these doubts beyond exception; and that is, That our Teachers have the <hi>Spirit.</hi> Friends! I have not any intention ever to be in Print again; unless I have a <hi>great</hi> and just provocation: And therefore let me beg leave; for a few lines in this matter: for many (very many) are here mistaken. They have the <hi>Spirit</hi> (say they:) But I ask, Have not others the Spirit <hi>as well</hi> as they? Will they limit and confine the Spirit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves? But they <hi>teach</hi> by the Spirit. What mean they by that? Can <hi>all</hi> that have the Spirit, teach (I mean publikely?) doth the Spirit enable <hi>all</hi> that have it, to do <hi>that?</hi> And those that cannot <hi>preach,</hi> have not they the Spirit? Doth the inbeing of the Spirit enable <hi>every one</hi> to <hi>all</hi> intents and purposes? They wo'nt be so <hi>shameless</hi> as to say so. What mean they then, when they say, they <hi>teach</hi> by the Spirit? I suppose they will say, As Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>teaches</hi> them, so they preach. And in so saying, they say <hi>well,</hi> if they well <hi>understand</hi> what they say. But then,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114647:36"/>how doth the Spirit <hi>teach</hi> them? Doth it teach them <hi>mediately</hi> or <hi>immediately;</hi> with, or without the <hi>Word?</hi> If they say, <hi>Without</hi> the Word; then they forsake their Colours, and go over to the tents of the <hi>Enthusiasts</hi> and <hi>Quakers.</hi> And that they wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt own (at least in open profession.) Well then: The Spirit teaches them <hi>by</hi> the Word. And indeed, this is the one and onely <hi>spiritual</hi> and most indubitable and infallible teaching<note n="*" place="margin">I mean as publick and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</note>, since the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apostles.</hi> For as for the Prophets; none of their Prophecies <hi>were of or from any private sense or interpretation of their own:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Per. 1.20, 21.</note>
                  <hi>But those holy men of God spake as they were moved, or carried out by the holy Spirit.</hi> And as for the Apostles;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note>
                  <hi>God who at the first creation caused the light to shine out of darkness, shined into their hearts, to give the light of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.</hi> And for the confirmation of the authenticalness of their Ministery, and the truth of their Doctrine,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3, 4.</note> God <hi>bore them witness from heaven, with signes and wonders, and with divers miracles and gifts of the holy spirit.</hi> So that now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prophets &amp; Apostles (their doctrine) are believers built, <hi>as upon the foundation; Christ himself being the chief corner-stone, in whom both meet, and all are united.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note> And hence, he that teaches <hi>Scripturally,</hi> teaches <hi>Spiritually.</hi> And such teachings and doctrines are <hi>Spiritual</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.4.</note> Being (not the <hi>enticing words</hi> of humane Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy, or wisdom of this world, but) the dictates of the holy Spirit. Thus far then we are agreed, if they be of this judgement: if not, let them speak <hi>out.</hi> Why then, if the Spirit teach them <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> or <hi>from</hi> the Word; I ask again, Doth it teach them by the bare outward <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (the sound) or by the <hi>sense</hi> and meaning of the word? I suppose they will not say, that bare <hi>sounds,</hi> without the <hi>sense</hi> or <hi>signification,</hi> inform any thing. Well then, how shall we come to the <hi>sense</hi> and signification of the <hi>words</hi> of Scripture? For if we can't come to the sense and signification of <hi>words,</hi> we cannot come to the sense and meaning of <hi>sentences;</hi> And so, not of what is delivered. How then (I say) will they come to the <hi>sense</hi> of words?
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114647:37"/>Will they say the <hi>Spirit</hi> teaches them to understand them? Was any man ever <hi>so</hi> taught, since the Apostles times? Or will they say, the Spirit teaches them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the meaning of <hi>sentences,</hi> without understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meaning of the <hi>words,</hi> of which the sentence doth consist? Doth the Spirit teach them (for instance) what the word <hi>justification,</hi> or <hi>adoption,</hi> means; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently other things that are <hi>dependent</hi> upon them? Who will step forth, and tell us, (and not lye) that he was <hi>so</hi> taught? But further, if they be taught by the Spirit to understand <hi>words;</hi> the Spirit can teach them to understand <hi>Latine,</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew:</hi> And the knowledge of them <hi>all</hi> (especially of the two last, in which the Scriptures were written) are necessary for a <hi>Teacher;</hi> so far at least, as to be, in <hi>some measure,</hi> able to compare words with words, and sentences with senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>other</hi> places of Scripture; for his better assurance in the truth of what he doth deliver, in cases or places <hi>doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ful.</hi> And this (I doubt not) was the Apostles meaning, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. when speaking of his way and <hi>manner</hi> of teaching, which he says was the <hi>Spirits teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> he did compare <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, spirituals with spirituals; spiritual words and sentences, one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: that so he might speak according to the rule and <hi>oanon.</hi> He would not speak contrary, to what the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> (who went before him) had delivered. And upon this account he <hi>justifies</hi> himself and his doctrine, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. <hi>I said</hi> (or taught) <hi>no other thing, then what Moses and the Prophets did say should come.</hi> And his hearers at <hi>Berea</hi> are accounted more noble, for comparing his <hi>doctrine</hi> with the <hi>Scripture, Acts</hi> 17.11. Now can our unlettered Teachers do this? Can they compare Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture with Scripture, in the language it was <hi>written?</hi> or doth the Spirit <hi>teach</hi> them so to do? will they say so? And for the Latine, (which is adopted into our native Language, and) in the words whereof <hi>much</hi> of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, in <hi>translation,</hi> is expressed; I dare be bold to say, and make it good, that for want of understanding it, they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114647:37"/>know not what they say: at least, they are not able to make good, explain, or <hi>maintain,</hi> what they deliver to the people: much less against an adversary. I'll instance in one of the words before mentioned; and so I might in divers other. The word <hi>justification,</hi> 'tis English now with us; and it is originally Latine. Now suppose a <hi>Papist</hi> come to deal with an <hi>unlettered</hi> Teacher, about the doctrine of <hi>Justification:</hi> And says this Teacher, I am justified not by any thing that I <hi>do,</hi> or that is <hi>in</hi> me; not by any <hi>inherent</hi> righteousness. No, (says the Papist?) let's examine what is <hi>justification:</hi> It's a <hi>Latine</hi> word, says he; what means it? <hi>Justificare,</hi> signifies <hi>justaw sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> to <hi>make</hi> a man just, or to <hi>make</hi> him righteous. This is more then to <hi>declare</hi> or <hi>pronounce</hi> a man righteous; it's a <hi>making</hi> a man righteous. And therefore the very <hi>word,</hi> the word of your own Bible (if you did understand it) is <hi>against</hi> you. Now what will <hi>Ignoramus</hi> say in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; if he be not able to shew (as he cannot) how that <hi>word</hi> is used in a sense farther <hi>removed,</hi> from its prime and original signification, in other places of Scripture, and <hi>prophane</hi> Authors<note n="*" place="margin">And that it is word borrowed from the Civil Law; wherein when a man is acquitted of a crime, with which he was charged, he is said to be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> conform to whom the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Scriptures <hi>often</hi> expresses himself, that he might be understood by those he speaks to: And yet not be <hi>limited</hi> to his expressions; whether to speak according to the <hi>first</hi> and original, or the <hi>second</hi> and borrowed sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the words: Thereby making <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> useful and needful, for understanding the Scriptures: And to let men see a necessity of <hi>painful</hi> Teachers; until the main question be resolved, namely, <hi>Doth the Spirit teach them to do this, without such assistances?</hi> And therefore I do aver, That whereas these men give out themselves as <hi>gifted</hi> brethren, and so fit for the work of the Ministery, 'tis no such matter. And I further affirm, that a man furnished with <hi>gifts</hi> of learning, and common grace, is fitter and better gifted for that work, then <hi>many</hi> who have saving grace by the sanctifying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and are <hi>not</hi> so gifted. And I yet further assert, that he who is <hi>so</hi> gifted, is taught (and may be truly said to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114647:38"/>teach) <hi>by</hi> the Spirit. For who is it (but the Spirit) that makes a man <hi>capable</hi> of learning? Is it not possible, that many of our undertakers (if they had been set to School) might not have proved Scholars? for, <hi>Ex quolibet ligno non fit Mercurius:</hi> A Long, will make but a Logger-head: And all are not Scholars that go to School, nor can be. And whence is the difference of <hi>ingenies,</hi> but from that Spirit, who dispenses all to all, even <hi>common</hi> graces, as well as <hi>saving;</hi> whether <hi>infused</hi> or <hi>acquired?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any shall suppose me to undervalue the <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and teachings of the Spirit; I do with all <hi>humble</hi> and adorable reverence bow my soul before the tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Majestie of my most <hi>dreadful</hi> Maker, and profess in his <hi>all-discerning</hi> presence, that I prize and value <hi>one</hi> grain of <hi>special</hi> grace, in order to my own salvation; before all the <hi>common</hi> gifts and endowments of Nature, Art, or Learning, in the world: with this <hi>belief</hi> also, That it is not so much (if at all) the Spirit in <hi>my heart</hi> as a Teacher,<note place="margin">As for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streperous b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the blasphemous Quakers, (they preach not by the Spirit) <hi>nihil mocor.</hi> Truth will justifie it self against all i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s adversaries.</note> as the Spirit with his <hi>own</hi> Word in the heart of the <hi>hearer,</hi> that doth promote <hi>his</hi> salvation. And for this point of the knowledge of the truths of Scripture, by a <hi>natural</hi> man, over and beyond what a truly-<hi>sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> person may know, and so be able to deliver; that I stand not <hi>alone</hi> in this judgement: And because many people are perswaded more by <hi>authority</hi> of persons then strength of Argument; I shall give you the affirmations of some, who are considerable in this matter.</p>
               <p>And the first is a Person of Honour;<note place="margin">Vindication of the Scriptures and Gospel-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, <hi>pag. 13, 14.</hi>
                  </note> the Lord <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> President of his Highness Council; the Work quoted in the margin: wherein he doth assert, that a <hi>natural man may be very able in understanding Scripture:</hi> and <hi>that</hi> upon this ground, because the <hi>literal and Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> sense, is the true sense of Scripture.</p>
               <p>The next is that industrious, and (to good purpose) laborious man. Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his Discourse of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits witness to the Truth of Christianity,</hi> pag. 172. wherein he says,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baxter</hi>'s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonableness of infidelity.</note>
                  <hi>You cannot name any Truth, which a gracious man knoweth, but an hypocrite may have a speculative knowledge
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:114647:38"/>of the same, and say the same words concerning it as he can.</hi> And that <hi>though the Spirit cause not the sanctified to know any more for number of truths, then an hypocrite may know; yet the commoner gists of the Spirit, by study and learning, cause many ungodly men to know many truths, which thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of the godly never knew.</hi> And there he tells you the end of the Spirits work in the godly, in these words: <hi>The Spirit of holiness</hi> (saith he) <hi>is not given to know more truths by, then an unsanctified man can know; but to know the same better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third is that eminent Doctor <hi>Owen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Treatise of mortification.</note> now Vice-Chancellor of the University of <hi>Oxford: The difference</hi> (saith he) <hi>between believers and unbelievers (as to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) is not so much in the matter of their knowledge, as in the manner of knowing. Unbelievers some of them may know more, and be able to say more of God, his perfections and his will, then many believers. The excellency</hi> (saith he) <hi>of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, is not that he hath a large apprehension of things: but that what he doth apprehend, (which perhaps may be very little) he sees it in the light of the Spirit of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another learned Pen that hath written so fully in this matter,<note place="margin">Balm to heal religious wounds, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to <hi>Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er's</hi> Pulpit-guard routed, by <hi>Ric. Saunders:</hi> printed for <hi>W. Adderten</hi> at the three golden Falcons in Duck lane, a small piece well worth reading.</note> that should I give you in all he speaks to this purpose, I should be too tedious; only I will give you <hi>one</hi> of his <hi>positions,</hi> which he backs with strong and clear <hi>reasons: There is not</hi> (saith he) <hi>any Scripture under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by spiritual Christians, the true Grammatical sence of which, a man that hath not the Spirit of Christ may not attain unto, by those outwards helps that are afforded to him. A notional knowledge of the sense of Scripture, is common to natural as well as spiritual men, else</hi> (saith he) <hi>knowledge were an infallible character of grace: which no body I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose will affirm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More Testimonies I might have produc'd which are <hi>ad manum;</hi> and more (I doubt not) might, which I have not ready to my hand: But what hath been is sufficient to discover, That the <hi>pretence</hi> of preaching by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> is but a <hi>pious fraud,</hi> in some men, to set up themselves in the hearts and consciences (and consequently in the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114647:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:114647:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:114647:40"/>purses) of people, as being more <hi>infallible and spiritual</hi> then others, when it's no such matter: no, nor so sure of Truch, nor so secure from Error neither. And therefore I draw up the result of all in this matter, in this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: <hi>The in-let and out-let, the fore and back-door of all our misery, is an ignorant, unlettered and contemptible Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the most part you shall know them by this badge and character: They are separating, factious and schismatical; and therefore to all <hi>sober</hi> Christians, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the caution and counsel of the Apostle: <hi>I beseech you brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17, 18</note>
                  <hi>for they that are such, serve not Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by good words and fair speeches, deceive the hearts of the simple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to you my Brethren, who are lawfully called to the work of the Ministery, though I be the least of ten thousand, yet let me minde you in the words of that great Apostle, and I have done: <hi>Take heed unto your selves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 20.28, 29, 30.</note>
                  <hi>and to all the flock over which the Holy Ghost hath made you overseers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchased with his own blood: for I know this, That after my departure shall grievous wolves enter in among you, not sparing the flock. Also of your own selves shall men ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se, speaking perverse things, to draw away Disciples after them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>